<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of the labour, travail and suffering of that faithful servant of the Lord Alice Curwen Who departed this life the 7th day of the 6th moneth, 1679. and resteth in peace with the Lord.</title>
            <author>Martindell, Anne.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52122</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M857</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215534</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827388</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827388</idno>
            <idno type="VID">31806</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52122)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31806)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1891:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of the labour, travail and suffering of that faithful servant of the Lord Alice Curwen Who departed this life the 7th day of the 6th moneth, 1679. and resteth in peace with the Lord.</title>
                  <author>Martindell, Anne.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 55, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Anne Martindell.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Includes testimonials by her husband, Thomas Curwen, and others.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Friends House Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Curwen, Alice, d. 1679 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Massachusetts --  Boston --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:31806:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RELATION OF THE Labour, Travail AND SUFFERING Of that faithful Servant of the Lord Alice Curwen.</p>
            <p>Who departed this Life the 7th Day of the 6th Moneth, 1679. and reſteth in Peace with the LORD.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Here is the Patience of the Saints, here are they that keep the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God, and the Faith of Jeſus,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. 14.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>The Souls of the Righteous are precious in the Eyes of the Lord, and they ſhall be had in Everlaſting Remembrance.</q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb facs="tcp:31806:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31806:2"/>
            <head>Something of <hi>Alice Curwen</hi>'s Teſtimony, which did lie upon her to declare ſome few dayes before ſhe departed out of the Body: ſhe ſpoke for one to come to write, and there was one that did come, and did purpoſe to write, but the Lord's Power and Preſence was ſo with her, that the Friends that were with her were ſo broken into Tenderneſs that there could nothing be written; but there was one Friend which was preſent with her at that time which did remember ſomething of what ſhe did ſpeak as followeth, whoſe Name is <hi>Anne Martindall.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AND I can truly ſay, my Heart was greatly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected and much broken in hearing of that pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Teſtimony which dear <hi>Alice Curmen</hi> did bear for the Lord, and for his Eternal Truth, and in the Senſe and Conſideration of that bleſſed heavenly Power, which did run thorow her at that time, my Spirit is often tendred as before the Lord; and truly many of her Words are paſt out of my Memory. The firſt time I did ſee her ſhe had been ſick about five dayes, and ſhe ſeemed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> but I went again <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> very ſick that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:31806:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:31806:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:31806:4"/>continued that Night, yet ſhe was very ſenſible, and deſired me to ſit up with her, and ſo I did ſtay all that Night, in which time ſhe did utter many preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Words, which I cannot call to mind; ſhe ſaid, <hi>That ſhe felt nothing upon her, but all was clear; for</hi> (ſhe ſaid) <hi>I do not know that ever I did any thing that did of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Lord, if it was but a Haſty word or a Thought, but I was reproved for it, and I was willing to lie low and wait upon the Lord until he was pleaſed to ariſe again:</hi> And ſhe ſpoke much of the Goodneſs of the Lord to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her, how that <hi>He had been with her at all times and in all places.</hi> Some asked her, <hi>If ſhe did think that ſhe ſhould not get over it?</hi> To which ſhe anſwered, <hi>I do not know what the Lord has to do; but I am freely given up to do his will, whatever it be, Life or Death, I am as clear as a Child:</hi> this ſhe ſpoke ſeveral times, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, <hi>that the will of the Lord might be done.</hi> And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhe had lain a while, ſhe ſaid, <hi>I have ſomething in my Mind to ſpeak, if the Lord will enable me;</hi> and ſhe ſpoke forth with a Heavenly Melody, and ſo ſpoke a long time, but I do remember very few of her words; but ſhe ſaid, <hi>The Lord is on his way, and he will go on Conquerings and to Conquer; and he will carry on his great work which he hath begun:</hi> And ſhe often deſired <hi>Friends to be faithful, and follow the Lord fully;</hi> and ſaid, <hi>That ſhe would have none to go before, nor none to ſtay behind, nor to turn aſide either to the Right Hand or to the Left, but follows the Lord your Leader whereſoever he goes:</hi> for ſhe had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Senſe upon her of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> know the Truth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>with us in a great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> were ſold it for
<pb facs="tcp:31806:4"/>the Preferment of this World, which will periſh and paſt away, and yet they can come in with us, and ſit down in Meetings, and have their Clothes made like the World's Faſhions, and like their order, and ſpeak their own Words; but the Lord will blow ſuch away with the Whirlewind of his Wrath: but thoſe that are faithful Travailers in the work of the Lord, the Lord will preſerve, though they may meet with many Tryals and Beſetments both inwardly and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly.</hi> And ſhe deſired, <hi>That all would let their Light ſhine, and none to put it under a Buſhel or under a Bed, but all ſtand faithful for the Lord in your Day, and then you need not be afraid of Death, but it will be as eaſie to you as it is to me.</hi> Truly ſhe was ſo filled with the Lord's bleſſed Power and living Preſence, that the Senſe of her Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was many times taken from her; and ſhe did of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſay, <hi>Truly Friends, I have little Pain upon me, only weak;</hi> and many a time ſhe did lie ſinging, and did make a ſweet Melody to the Lord, when ſhe uttered very few words, except on this wiſe, <hi>Oh my Heavenly Father! how haſt thou filled my Cup, and made it to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow! for I can do no leſs but even praiſe and magnifie they holy eternal Name:</hi> and ſo ſhe often deſired, <hi>That the Will of the Lord might be done, whether it was Life or Death;</hi> and ſaid, <hi>For to me to live is Chriſt and to dye is Gain:</hi> and many ſuch like precious words, which ſhe did ſpeak, which I cannot call to mind. She ſpoke many very clear weighty things concerning the Virgins and their Lamps, and exhorted all to be diligent, and to know Life and Virtue in themſelves to feed upon; for ſhe ſaid, <hi>The time will come that Words will ceaſe, and Life ſhall more ariſe;</hi> and many more weighty things ſhe did ſpeak, and ſaid if ſhe did live ſhe muſt declare it, and
<pb facs="tcp:31806:5"/>
               <hi>if ſhe did dye ſhe muſt leave it as a Teſtimony for the Lord:</hi> ſhe often deſired Friends <hi>to be faithful to the Lord, and follow the Lord fully, as</hi> Deborah <hi>and</hi> Baruk <hi>did; which if all had ſtood faithful, what a bleſſed Day would it have been ere now!</hi> So when ſhe had declared and ſpoken what was upon her Spirit, ſhe had ſome eaſe, and ſo continued about two hours; and ſhe ſpoke very much of her Off ſpring, and ſaid, <hi>She deſired nothing more concerning them, then that they may Fear the Lord, and then they will never Want.</hi> And then towards the latter end of the Night ſhe had an extream great Pain in her Head, which was very hard to bear, yet in all this time ſhe did not utter one unpatient word, but was like a patient Lamb, and ſaid, <hi>Friends, breathe to the Lord for me, that he may lay no more upon me than I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to bear, that I may not offend this good God:</hi> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ſhe did breathe forth in Prayer to the Lord; then ſhe had a little Eaſe, and lay ſtill, as if ſhe had been in a Slumber, and a little after ſhe ſaid, <hi>I have been in the Deep, and I had ſomething to ſpeak, but I could not.</hi> So ſhe did grow weaker and weaker, but ſhe was ſweetly carryed through it to the End.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This was declared of this faithful Servant of the Lord, who ſaid,</hi> She would have none to mourn for her when ſhe was gone.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Names of them that were with her:</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>Mary Nelſon,</item>
                  <item>Marvell Fallbery,</item>
                  <item>Alice Cobb,</item>
                  <item>Rebecca Reckly,</item>
                  <item>Anne Martindall,</item>
                  <item>Thomas Curwen <hi>the elder,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Thomas Curwen <hi>the younger,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Thomas Cobb.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb facs="tcp:31806:5"/>
            <head>Thomas Curwen HIS TESTIMONY, Which is in behalf of his Wife's Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, which ſhe did bear faithfully for God and for his Eternal Truth ever ſince ſhe was Convinced, and her Heart and Mind turned from Darkneſs to the Light of Jeſus Chriſt, and from Satan's Power to the Power of God, who did ſerve the Lord in Fear, and rejoyced with Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling whilſt Breath and Life remained.</head>
            <head type="sub">And Bleſſed are the Dead, that Dye in the Lord; they do Reſt from their Labours, and their Works do follow them.</head>
            <p>AND this I can ſay to the Praiſe and Glory of our God, That ſhe did Dye in the Lord; for ſhe did Praiſe and magnifie the Name of the Lord, and was freely given up to dye; and the Lord's Preſence was with her, which did carry her
<pb facs="tcp:31806:6"/>up above her Weakneſs in the Fleſh: and though ſhe be dead, and her Body return to the Duſt, yet her Spirit is alive, where Hell, Death and the Grave can never ſeperate us; Glory to our God forever, who is the God of the Living, and not of the Dead; and the Living Praiſe the Lord, the Dead in the Grave of Sin cannot; <hi>For the Wages of Sin is Death, but the Gift of God is Eternal Life:</hi> and bleſſed are they that know the Gift of God, and have their Minds exerciſed in it, or elſe it had been better for them they had never known it; but as their Minds are exerciſed in the Gift of God, they come to witneſs Redemption from Sin and Death, and come to witneſs Eternal Life, where the Redeemed of the Lord do rejoyce, who are redeemed out of the Earth, and have a Habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Heaven; and the Redeemed do ſing Praiſes and Halelujahs to the Lord God and the Lamb forever and for evermore, over Death, Hell and the Grave; for he is riſen whom the Grave could not hold, Glory to our God forever, to whom all Power is given both in Heaven and in Earth, and he will rule all with his Iron Rod, everlaſting Praiſes forever be given unto his holy &amp; bleſſed Name, the Lamb of God, who was ſlain from the Foundation of the world, by whom the world was made, who was dead, but he is alive, whoſe Name is called <hi>The word of God,</hi> who was in the World, and the World knew him not; <hi>And ye will not come to me</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>that ye may have Life;</hi> who hath given us Life, Breath and Being, that we may live to his Praiſe, and to his Honour and Glory forever, who is worthy, who is worthy forever and for evermore, ſaith my Soul.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:31806:6"/>
            <p>And this I can ſay concerning my dear and loving Wife, who was dear and tender over me, to ſerve me in any thing that might do me good either for Soul or Body; and the Conſideration of her endeared Love to me doth often times come very freſh into my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, which doth break my Heart into much Tenderneſs, which doth cauſe me to write theſe few Lines concerning God's Teſtimony, which ſhe did bear for his Eternal Truth: And I can truly ſay, <hi>She was given me of the Lord;</hi> who was a Meet Help for me, who did live Husband and Wife about Thirty Eight Years, who was my true Friend and Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in Tribulation, who did keep the Word of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience in the Day of Tryal and in the Hour of Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and did bear the Burthen in the heat of the Day without Murmuring, or looking back to the Fleſh-Pots of <hi>Egypt,</hi> but did Rejoyce in Tribulation: <hi>Know ye not</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that Tribulation worketh Patience, and Patience Experience, and Experience Hope, and this Hope maketh not aſhamed, becauſe we have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the End of our Hope, which is, Salvation to be as Walls and Bulwarks:</hi> And now we can ſay to the Praiſe and Glory of our God, <hi>That now is Salvation nearer than when we firſt believed.</hi> And when a meaſure of the Spirit of Grace was manifeſted to her, and ſhe did feel the Operation of it working in her Heart, and was led and guided by it, Oh! how ſhe did improve her Talent for the Lord! and for one Talent he gave her more; and the Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt did teach her to deny all Ungodlineſs and Worldly Luſts, and to live Soberly, and Righteouſly, and Godly in this World; and ſhe did grow in the Grace
<pb facs="tcp:31806:7"/>of God from Strength to Strength, and from Grace to Grace; and her Affections were not on things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, but on things above: for her Treaſure was in Heaven, where neither Ruſt nor Moth could corrupt, nor Thieves break through and Steal; and the Lord was her Portion, who is the Portion of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: And when ſhe was got into the higheſt Form of Profeſſion, ſhe was very Zealous in her Way and Form, that when the Truth came, ſhe was ready to receive it, who did receive it with great Joy and Glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heart, and ſaid, <hi>Now I have found him whom my Soul loves, which was my Deſire, which the blind watch-men could never know in reading of the Scriptures of Truth:</hi> She had much comfort in reading of <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms, which was much Refreſhment to her to ſound forth Praiſes to the Lord; and ſhe did ſing with the Spirit, and with Underſtanding; and ſhe was almoſt alwayes Praiſing the Lord, and magnifying his holy and bleſſed Name; and when ſhe could not ſpeak, ſhe put her Hands together, and did lift them up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, and did Praiſe the Lord in her Heart: And when the Lord did ſend her forth to preach the Everlaſting Goſpel, ſhe did not reaſon with Fleſh and Blood; for the Lord's Power and Preſence was with her, wherein ſhe did ſound forth his Praiſes to the Nations, and did declare of the Wonderful Works which the Lord had done for the Sons and Daughters of Men: And ſhe was not aſhamed to confeſs the Name of the Lord before men, who was brought ſeveral times before <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> and <hi>Rulers,</hi> and was caſt into <hi>Priſon,</hi> and was ſet in the <hi>Stocks,</hi> and brought to the <hi>Whipping-Poſt</hi> for her Teſtimony,
<pb facs="tcp:31806:7"/>which ſhe had to bear for the Lord, and for his Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Truth; for ſhe did follow Chriſt Jeſus fully, who was the Captain of her Salvation, and did make War in Righteouſneſs with the Beaſt and the Falſe Prophet, and her Captain did never fail her in time of Need, but did go before her, and did tread down her Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies as Aſhes under her Feet, and the Lamb did get the Victory; Glory to our God forever, who did plead the Cauſe of the Innocent, and did put a Word in her Mouth in every needful time; and the Lord was with her, and his Eternal Arm and Power did cover her Head in the Day of Battel: And ſhe did often pray to the Lord, and ſaid, <hi>Lord, let me injoy thy Preſence, and I deſire no more;</hi> and the Lord did hear her Cry, and did anſwer her Deſire; for the Love of God was ſo large unto her, which is more than I can expreſs; Glory and Everlaſting Praiſes be unto the Lord. And ſhe had great Exerciſe with the Prieſts of this Nation, and other Nations and Iſlands beyond the Seas, and did go in the Fear &amp; Dread of the Lord to ſeveral Prieſts &amp; Steeple-houſes, and the Lord was with her, and gave her Dominion, who went in the Name of the Lord: and ſhe did not matter how Great they were, nor how High they had builded <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel;</hi> for ſhe was over them all in the Fear and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God; for ſhe was a Dread and a Terror to the Wicked where-ever ſhe came: <hi>For the Wicked could not ſtand in Judgment, nor Sinners in the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Righteous.</hi> She did diſcover the Seat of the Beaſt and the Whore, who doth ſit upon the Waters, with a Golden Cup in her Hand full of Abomination, which all the World wonder after,
<pb facs="tcp:31806:8"/>who have the Mark of the Beaſt in their Hand and in their Fore head. And ſhe had a true Senſe of the Prieſts ſpirit, and did know and diſcover them let them come under what Pretence they would; for ſhe did eſteem the Lords Truth above all, &amp; would not have neglected any Opportunity whereby ſhe might have been ſerviceable for the Lord; for it was her Meat &amp; Drink to do the Will of God, who did receive her Reward in a large meaſure; for there are ſome that received thirty fold, and ſome ſixty, but ſhe did receive an hundred fold in this Life, and in the World to come Life Everlaſting; for it was much Joy and Gladneſs of Heart to her in meeting to meet with the Lord and his People in the bleſſed Unity of the Spirit, where the Lord is Worſhipped; and the Lord did fill her Cup to the overflowing to others, who would never have eaten her Morſel alone, but would have others to have eaten and drunk with her, which was to the great Refreſhment and Edifying and Building up of others in the Faith of the Elect; for her Cry was to the Lord, <hi>That all who were called might be elected and choſen Veſſels of Honour for the Lord;</hi> for her Joy was full in the Lord, and ſhe did ſound forth Living Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Praiſes to the God of her Life, and did Magnifie his great Name while ſhe did live in her Earthly Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, which ſhe did give freely up to be laid in the Duſt; and the Heavenly Tabernacle of Grace was with her, which God had pitched, and not Man; and the Lord put a New Song in her Mouth, which none could ſing but the Redeemed of the Lord, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhe did often in ſecret breathe forth Praiſes to the Lord; for the Lord's Preſence was with her, wherein
<pb facs="tcp:31806:8"/>ſhe could not contain her ſelf, but ſhe breathed forth Praiſes to the Lord, which did refreſh the tender Plants of the Lord when ſhe had no Words to ſpeak. But when ſhe did ſpeak, ſhe did ſpeak from the Mouth of the Lord, and did blow the Trumpet in <hi>Sion,</hi> and did ſound forth an Alarm in the Holy Mount, which made the Inhabitants of the Earth to tremble; for the Lion of the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> did roar out of <hi>Sion,</hi> and the Trumpet did give a certain ſound, whereby ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny were awakened, and their Minds turned from Darkneſs to the Light; and the Day did ſpring from on High, which did give Light to them that had long ſitten in Darkneſs, and under the Shadow of Death, whoſe Feet were guided in the Way of Peace; who was inſtrumental to bring many from under the Wo, whoſe Feet were ſet upon the Rock; and ſhe did not deſpiſe the Day of ſmall things, but was alwayes bringing up the hindermoſt of the Flock, as <hi>Jacob</hi> did; and ſhe would have ſtooped for the leaſt Grain for the gathering of the Seed out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> where it did not grow, which was under <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s hard-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Task-maſters, and was oppreſt as a Cart was preſt with Sheaves: And her Converſation was as becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Goſpel; for her Children and many more were Convinced by her Wiſe Walking before them, in the Wiſdom of God; for ſhe had a great Care of her Off-ſpring, to bring them up in the Fear of the Lord, and did often breathe to the Lord for them, and the Lord did hear her Cry, and did anſwer her Deſire; and I can ſay to the Praiſe and Glory of our God, that the Lord hath had Regard to them, and hath done wonderfully for them, who hath gathered
<pb facs="tcp:31806:9"/>them home unto himſelf, out of the Vain Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World, and hath placed his Fear in their Hearts; <hi>For a Mother may forget her Sucking-Child, but the Lord doth not forget them:</hi> Oh! what Cauſe have we to return Praiſe, Honour and Glory to the Lord forever, who is worthy forever and for evermore. And in all Places and Countries where-ever ſhe came, ſhe exhorted Friends, <hi>To have a Care of their Children, &amp; to bring them up in the Fear of the Lord, ſo that from one Generation to another the Lord's Truth may ſpread, and cover the Earth as the Waters cover the Sea, and that the Lord's Teſtimony may not fall, and that his great Name may be exalted over all, to the Praiſe and Glory of our God forever:</hi> For ſhe was ſingly given up to do whatever might be for the Proſperity of God's Eternal Truth. Her Labour and Travail was very great, wherein ſhe did ſpend her ſelf, and was ſpent for the Seed's ſake, that did ſuffer under great Oppreſſion. And ſhe did preach the Goſpel freely, without Money and without Price; for the Goſpel was to be preached freely: Therefore away with all Hirelings, who preach for Hire and divine for Money, who keep Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple alwayes learning, and never come to the Truth: For ſhe did deſire no man's Gold, or Silver, or Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel; for ſhe had the Lord for her Portion, and ſhe deſired no more; for her Habitation was in Heaven, and her Dwelling was in Eternity, where ſhe did live and move, and had her eternal Being; <hi>For no other Foundation can any man lay, than that which is already laid, which is Chriſt Jeſus, the Rock of Ages, the Foundation of many Generations,</hi> which ſhe did build upon, not Hay, nor Stubble, nor Gold, nor Silver, nor Precious
<pb facs="tcp:31806:9"/>Stones; for all theſe will burn when the heat of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution comes; but ſhe did witneſs a ſpiritual Houſe made up of Living Stones, and the Top-Stone was laid, which is the Ground and Pillar of Truth; for ſhe had finiſhed up her Teſtimony, and laid down her Head in Reſt and Peace with the Lord. And ſhe did exhort Friends in her Travail in the Service of the Lord, <hi>To Mind their Latter-End, and be ready and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for Death; for when Death comes, you may have enough to do to dye; that ye be not like the Fooliſh Virgins, who had no Oyl in their Lamps, againſt whom the Door was ſhut.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now the Lambs War is accompliſhed, and the Lamb hath got the Victory, who hath made War in Righteouſneſs, and hath overcome and gotten the Victory over the Beaſt and the Falſe Prophet, the Lamb of God, that taketh away the Sins of the World, who was ſlain from the Foundation of the World; and while the World has a Foundation in man's Heart, who was dead, but is now alive, whoſe Name is called the Word of God: Praiſes, Praiſes endleſs, pure, living, eternal Praiſes be given, aſcribed, rendred and returned by all the faithful Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of the Lamb, as this faithful Servant of the Lord hath done <hi>Alice Curwen.</hi> Praiſes, Praiſes, end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Praiſes be given to the Lord God and the Lamb forever and for evermore, ſaith my Soul, and the Souls of the Righteous, who are travelling on in the New and Living Way, which is the Way of Life and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; Glory, Honour and Everlaſting Praiſes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever and for evermore.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:31806:10"/>
            <p>And this little Teſtimony I do not write in any way, but that it might be upon Record for Ages and Generations to come, and that every Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony that is from the Right Seed may be kept, and that not one Grain be loſt, that the Bleſſing of the Lord may be with us and with our Poſterity forever, which was the Deſire of my dear Wife.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Curwen.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb facs="tcp:31806:10"/>
            <head>Alice Cobb<hi>'s Teſtimony concerning her Mother</hi> Alice Curwen.</head>
            <p>OH, my dearly beloved Mother! though ſhe be gone from us, and her Body in the Bowels of the Earth doth lie, yet to me her <hi>Memorial</hi> will never dye, and to thouſands more of the faithful ones; for indeed her Labour hath been great (both in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and other Nations and Iſlands) to gather many from Darkneſs to the Light, in which ſhe did walk; and in her Day did bear a <hi>noble Teſtimony for the Lord God and his Truth:</hi> She was freely given up to ſpend &amp; be ſpent in and for the Service of the Truth; <hi>for ſhe thought nothing too dear nor too near to part with or from, but was freely given up to follow the Lord what way ſoever he did call her to go:</hi> and ſhe did preach the Truth very powerfully, and in God's Authority did ſhe go on, <hi>not mattering what man could do unto her;</hi> for indeed the Lord was with her in every Exerciſe &amp; Tryal; for her Labour was great, but ſhe did know the Lord to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port her, and to lift up her Head above the <hi>many waters;</hi> for indeed before <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>Governours,</hi> though they were never ſo great, ſhe was bold and valient for the Lord &amp; his Truth. And as for us her tender Children, our Loſs is great; <hi>for ſhe was a tender Mother to us indeed;</hi> and ſhe did in her <hi>wiſe Walking</hi> and her <hi>harmleſs Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation</hi> preach to us daily; for truly her Life was all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long as it was now upon her Sick-Bed, breathing to the
<pb facs="tcp:31806:11"/>Lord God for her Off-ſpring, <hi>That they might live to his Praiſe:</hi> and ſhe prayed to the Lord very powerfully, and in as much ſtrength as in her Health, <hi>That if the Lord ſee it good to remove her, that he would lay no more upon her than he would give her Patience to bear, that ſo whether ſhe lived or dyed it might be to the Honour and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Lord God:</hi> and the Lord did give her Patience, for there came not an <hi>unpatient word</hi> out of her Mouth in all the time of her Sickneſs, but was exceedingly filled with the good Power and Preſence of the Lord our God; for ſhe lay making ſweet Melody to the Lord when ſhe could not ſpeak: &amp; a little before her Speech was taken away from her I asked my dear Mother, <hi>How art thou now? and how doſt thou feel thy ſelf? I fear thou art worſe than thou waſt:</hi> and her Anſwer was, <hi>My dear Child, be not troubled for me; I am very Eaſie, and have little Pain upon me, but Weakneſs.</hi> And ſo all along the Power and Preſence of the Lord did keep her and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve her, to the great Refreſhment and Conſolation of thoſe that were with her. And ſo the <hi>Memorial</hi> of my endeared Mother can never be forgotten by me</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Alice Cobb.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb facs="tcp:31806:11"/>
            <head>A Teſtimony concerning <hi>Alice Curwen.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Enemies of Truth among other Devices of the Devil, beſet the Son of God with hard Queſtions, thereby to enſnare him, one which is brought to my Bemem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance was, to oppoſe the <hi>Reſurrection of the Dead;</hi> and the Son of God to reprove it ſayes, <hi>God is the God of</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, <hi>the God of</hi> Iſaac, <hi>and of</hi> Jacob; <hi>and not the God of the Dead, but of the Living:</hi> This Anſwer left that Ranting Generation of the Saduces as blind as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound them; but the Living thereby then learned, and are now ſtrengthned in aſſurance of Faith, that He, Chriſt, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection and the Life is riſen, and alive, and lives for evermore; and who of this Life hath part, the Second Death hath no power over. So I ſpeak not the Praiſe of the Dead, but of the Living, which in Spirit the Righteous have fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with when the outward Veſſel is going or gone to Duſt, as this Servant of the Lord is known to me more by her Life and Teſtimony than by any outward Acquaintance; &amp; being with her on her Dying-Bed, though I heard not ſo much as ſome about her did, I could not but take notice of her Reſignedneſs to God's Will, though ſhe ſhewed to me her Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſs to take any Medicine, not chuſing any thing but the Will of God, to which ſhe freely gave up, though ſhe ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not very Aged, and but a few dayes before appeared a healthy ſtrong Woman, and was ſo; and as her Deſire and Endeavour was freely to declare what ſhe received of the Spirit of Life, and in this ſhe lives, and in this ſtands the
<pb facs="tcp:31806:12"/>Fellowſhip and Communion of the Saints, whether in theſe earthly Bodies, or out of them, and in this ſtands my Unity with her. And a near Relation of this deceaſed <hi>Alice Curwen</hi> ſhewing me a Paper writ by one with her in her Sickneſs, and asked me, <hi>If I could add any thing to it; for he intended to print it?</hi> and in my mind I had not much for printing it, there being not much Prophecy in it, and ſo put it off, not purpoſing to do any thing to it: But upon my Bed that Night or towards Morning, when in ſtillneſs was ſet before me the Bleſſing of <hi>Abraham, God's Friend, and his Portion was to Dye in Peace, and this thou art a Witneſs this good Woman did; and doſt thou think it ſmall to be teſtified to when thou ſeeſt ſo many Reſtleſs Impatient Ones toſſed, and crying for Help to Phyſicians of no value, and can find no Reſt?</hi> Then ſaid I, <hi>Let me Dye as ſhe has done; for I feel it a bleſſed End to Dye in Peace; for Prophecy has and muſt ceaſe, and Torgaes fail, but the Peace that is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us of Chriſt Jeſus is Everlaſting:</hi> So in the Spirit is witneſſed the Bond of Peace, to bind up together in the Bundle of Life, which Hell nor Death can never break, and here is the Heaven where no Unrighteous enter, but the Sanctified rejoyce together therein for evermore.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="relation">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:31806:12"/>
            <head>A RELATION OF THE <hi>Labour, Travail</hi> and <hi>Suffering</hi> OF Alice Curwen.</head>
            <p>THE 10th day of the 11th moneth, 1677 when I was retired in my Mind waiting upon the Lord, it was opened in my Heart by the inviſible Power of the living God, the vertue of which I felt, and the Springs of Life being witneſſed, I was moved to write of the Dealings of the Lord with me, and of my Travels and of my Teſtimony in writing, ſince I went from my outward Being; and what I had received from Friends in writing, of the good Succeſs, and Bleſſing, and Preſence of the inviſible God, who moves in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, and is now come to reward his People openly; Everlaſting Holy Praiſes be breathed forth and ſounded out unto the Lord our God for all his Mercies, for they are manifold at this day, therefore doth my Soul in ſecret bleſs his holy Name, who alone is worthy. And whilſt I queſtioned in my Mind, Why I ſhould write, fearing the Subtilty of the Enemy, and alſo not minding to keep Copies of ſeveral Papers that had been written, yet as I waited patiently to ſee my Clearneſs, it was ſaid in the ſecret
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:31806:13"/>of my Heart, <hi>What thou haſt kept, write:</hi> but I fearing ſaid with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my ſelf, <hi>Why ſhould it be known?</hi> and the Anſwer was, <hi>For the Encouragement of them that hereafter may put their Truſt in the Lord:</hi> and then I was made willing to write as followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="text">
                        <p>IN the year 1660. I hearing of the great Tribulation that the Servants of the Lord did ſuffer in <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> of cruel Whippings, of Bonds and Impriſonments, yea, to the laying down of their natural Lives; <hi>four Friends</hi> being Hanged there for their Teſtimony to God's bleſſed weighty Truth, againſt a Wicked Generation, which remains there un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til this day; I, at the hearing of their Patient Sufferings, my Heart was broken, and my Spirit deeply affected with Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Goodneſs of the Lord, who bears up the Spirits of them that truly fear him, and are willing to give up all that is near and dear, and to follow the Lamb whitherſoever he leads; and my Spirit was comforted in the bleſſed inviſible Power: but it was ſaid in the ſecret of my Heart, <hi>That I ſhould travail in that Nation, and ſee that Bloody Town of</hi> Boſton; at which my Heart was exceedingly broken, and I cryed unto the Lord with many Tears, and ſaid, <hi>O Lord, what ſhall become of my little Children, and of my poor Husband?</hi> (he being then in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for Tythe) and I mourned many dayes in a ſenſe of my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ability; yet at that time I could truly ſay, <hi>Thy bleſſed Will be done; let me enjoy thy Preſence, and keep me in thy Heavenly Power, and I deſire no more:</hi> ſo the thing was weighty upon me, but I kept it unto my ſelf, not knowing how it would be brought to paſs, conſidering in my mind the Lord might try me, whether I would give up or not; and as I found a Willingneſs, the thing was made eaſie, and the Burden taken away, whereupon I thought the Lord would accept my Willingneſs, and it was hid from me for a ſeaſon; but I can truly ſay in my meaſure, and that to the Praiſe of God, that I hid the Word of the Lord in my Heart until it was as a Fire in me till I had declared it, and I then told it to my Husband, the Power being freſh in me, and the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:31806:13"/>Love of God filled my Heart, in which I had true Unity with Friends in <hi>New-England;</hi> and I told my Husband, <hi>That the Lord would deliver him out of Priſon, and that we muſt travail in another Nation together, and there bear a Teſtimony to God's bleſſed Truth, which is broken forth in this Day of his Power, wherein he is making his People willing:</hi> And though we were then, and are at this day the leaſt of many of the Lord's Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, yet his Strength hath been manifeſted in Weakneſs, for which we have cauſe to bleſs his holy Name whilſt we have a day to live. So the thing reſted in my Heart many Moneths and Years, and then the Lord delivered my Husband out of Priſon, in which time my little Children were grown up, all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the youngeſt, which the Lord took away from me; then the Springs of Life opened in me, and the time was come that I might no longer hide it in my Heart, but make it known to Friends, which after I had done ſo, in opening my Heart a little to ſome Friends, the thing ſeemed harder to me to get through than before, in which time I was in a great ſtrait, but the Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, and it was ſaid ſecretly, that <hi>If I did go, I ſhould feel my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward from the Lord in my own Boſom:</hi> then I having this Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſealed in my Heart, I laboured with my Husband day and night to know his Mind, becauſe it was much with me, <hi>that we were to Travail together;</hi> but he did not yet ſee it to be required of him at that time, but gave me Liberty in Obedience to the Inviſible Power, though the thing was hard, becauſe it was ſhewed me at firſt, <hi>that we ſhould Travail together;</hi> but the Lord made me willing to leave all (that was near and dear to me) and I went on my Journey towards <hi>London,</hi> and after ſome time had with Friends there, I made Preparation to go to Sea, and having got my Bed and Clothes on board the Ship, it pleaſed the Lord (in whom was and is my Truſt) to ſend my Husband to go along with me: and ſo we took ſhipping together, and were thirteen Weeks in our Paſſage from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Road-Iſland</hi> belonging to <hi>New-England;</hi> and I can truly ſay, I did not know what I might do; for all there were in an Uproar, Killing, and Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Murdering, and great Diſtreſs was upon the Peoples Minds; and I ſaid in my Heart, <hi>The Lord that hath brought me
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:31806:14"/>out of my Native Country, lead me whither thou wilt; let me but enjoy thy Power and feel thy Preſence, and I deſire no more.</hi> So we ſtayed a few dayes in that Iſland, and were refreſhed with Friends; and we heard of a new Law that was made at <hi>Boſton</hi> againſt the People of God called <hi>Quakers,</hi> which Law was as followeth, (viz.)
<q>It was ordered at their Court at <hi>Boſton</hi> and the Authority thereof, That every Perſon found at a <hi>Quakers</hi> Meeting ſhall be apprehended <hi>(Ex Officio)</hi> by the Conſtable, &amp;c. by Warrant from a Magiſtrate or Commiſſioner, and ſhall be committed to the Houſe of Correction, and there to have the Diſcipline of the Houſe applyed unto them, and to be kept to work with Bread and Water for Three Dayes, and then releaſed; or elſe ſhall pay Five Pounds in Money as a Fine for ſuch an Offence (to the Collony) and all Conſtables neglecting their Duty, in not faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully executing this Order, ſhall incur the Penalty of Five Pounds upon Conviction.</q>
                        </p>
                        <p>And then it opened in us in the Springs of Life, <hi>That We muſt travail thither, and break in upon their new Law;</hi> in which we were willing to bear our Teſtimony, with the reſt of Friends, to God's bleſſed weighty Truth, againſt this Generation, that remain there unto this day, that ſo with thereſt of the Lord's People, we might fill up the Sufferings that remain behind, that ſo the Righteous Blood ſhed by this Generation may come upon them, which they ſhall not eſcape. So we travailed through the Woods and Places where the devouring <hi>Indians</hi> had made great Deſolation in many Places, but the Lord preſerved us, and we came to <hi>Boſton,</hi> and on the Firſt Day of the Week we had a Meeting with Friends there, and their Law not being yet publiſhed, we had our Liberty and our Meeting peaceable, and afterward, travailed Eaſtward near One Hundred Miles, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited Friends, and ſought them out where they were ſcattered becauſe of the great Diſtreſs of the <hi>Indians</hi> War, ſo that they had not had a Meeting to wait upon the Lord for ſeveral moneths before: ſo we travailed Eaſtward as far as <hi>Great-Iſland,</hi> and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:31806:14"/>
                           <hi>Piſcattoway</hi> River, and <hi>Dover,</hi> and ſeveral other places, and came to a Friend's Houſe beyond the River, where there were about two hundred people (ſome Friends, and others) who were come thither for Safety, and had fortified the Houſe very ſtrongly about for fear of theſe Bloody <hi>Indians,</hi> which had killed two of our Friends within three miles of that place; there we had ſeveral good Meetings, and the Preſence of the Lord was with us, and it was a time of great Diſtreſs, both Friends and others received our Teſtimony gladly; for it was a needful time; and the Power of the Lord was with us, and was our Support, for which we cannot but bleſs his Name whilſt we have a Being. Then we travailed again towards <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton,</hi> and viſiting Friends all along, and ſo came to <hi>Boſton</hi> again, where being in our Meeting, their Law being now publiſhed, the Conſtable with others came forcibly and drave us out of our Meeting all along the Street, until they came to the Priſon, or <hi>Houſe of Correction,</hi> whereinto they thruſt us; but the Lord was with us, and our Service there was great; for many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, both rich and poor, came to look upon us, and ſome were convinced, it being a time of great Tribulation, their Hearts failed for fear, and God's Witneſs was reached, Praiſes to God forever: And the third day of our Impriſonment they brought us down to the Whipping-Poſt, but the Preſence of the Lord was manifeſted there, which gave us Dominion over all their Cruelty, and we could not but Magnifie the Name of the Lord, and declare of his Wonderful Work at that time, at which the <hi>Heathen</hi> were aſtoniſhed, and ſhook their Heads: And the next day we were ſet at liberty, and went to our Meeting again (from which place they did fetch us to Priſon before) and we had a good Meeting peaceably, and took leave of Friends, and ſo we parted; and we came to <hi>Sittuate,</hi> and <hi>Dukesberry,</hi> and to <hi>Sandwich,</hi> and did viſit Friends all along in ſeveral places until we came to <hi>Road-Iſland;</hi> and after a little time ſpent with Friends there, it was with us to go into the Weſt part of <hi>New-England,</hi> to <hi>Shelter-Iſland</hi> and <hi>Long-Iſtand, Oyſter-Bay, Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi> and <hi>Eaſtcheſter,</hi> and to <hi>Graveſend,</hi> and a Place there cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Jamaco,</hi> and <hi>Matunicock,</hi> and <hi>New-York,</hi> and ſome part of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:31806:15"/>
                           <hi>New-Jarſey,</hi> ſo far as Friends did inhabit to our Knowledge, when we were there: in this time of our Paſſage thither we were ſeveral times put on Shore, the Wind not being for us, where we had good Service for the Lord and for his Truth, where there were no Friends, upon the main Land, at a place called <hi>New-London,</hi> and <hi>Seabrook,</hi> and <hi>Milford;</hi> then we did return unto the Yearly Meeting in <hi>Road-Iſland;</hi> and then <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mudus</hi> and <hi>Barbadoes</hi> were before us, and we would gladly have got a Paſſage to <hi>Bermudus,</hi> but could not, but a Paſſage to <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>badoes</hi> was near ready at that time, at the hearing of which I was afraid, and great Fear fell upon me, conſidering my own Weakneſs, and the Highneſs of all ſorts of people there, and fearing leſt they ſhould even trample upon my little Teſtimony, and leſt I ſhould ſuffer Loſs; and I, like <hi>Jonah</hi> in his day, would have fled, but there was no Hiding-place but in the Arm of the Lord, which was to me, and is to all that believe and obey a ſtrong Tower; <hi>Everlaſting Bleſſing, Glory and Honour be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed unto his great Name, to whom doth belong the Glory for all his Mercies, and that for evermore.</hi> And ſuch as may read this <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle,</hi> may believe that it was the Lord that put it into my Heart to write it, <hi>for the Encouragement of them that hereafter maytruſt in the Lord.</hi> So my Husband having much upon him to <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does,</hi> Friends accompanied us on Shipboard, where we had a bleſſed good Meeting before we parted, and in Five Weeks and Two Dayes we came to <hi>Barbadoes.</hi> And the next day after we came aſhore was their Quarterly-Meeting, where our Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny was gladly received; and we travailed in that Iſland about Seven Moneths, where we had good Service both amongſt Whites and Blacks; and the Lord added unto our Talent ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Talent more; Everlaſting Praiſes (ſaith our Souls in ſecret) unto his moſt holy Name, who hath given us good Succeſs, and is adding unto his Church ſuch as ſhall be ſaved in every Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for many did gather unto our Meetings: and we viſited ſome of their Prieſts, and invited them to our Meetings, ſome by Word, and ſome by Writing. And when we were clear in our Spirits of this Iſland, we would gladly have gone to <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mudus,</hi> but could not get a Paſſage, and then we found Freedom
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:31806:15"/>to write to Friends in that Iſland, and ſo to return home; and after we had taken leave of Friends in the Freedom of our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits we took Shipping, and came for <hi>London,</hi> where we arrived the ſame day Seven Weeks after we came from <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> which was the beginning of the third moneth, 1677. And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we had ſeen Friends at <hi>London,</hi> it was ſecretly in our Hearts, that we muſt viſit all the Meetings upon the Sea Coaſt Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward unto the Lands-End; and now ſince we had performed that Service, it was upon us to viſit ſome Meetings Eaſtward; and the good Preſence of the Lord hath been with us, for which Cauſe we have good Cauſe to bleſs his holy Name whilſt we have a day to live.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Now, in regard we could not meet with a Paſſago to <hi>Bermu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> neither from <hi>Road-Iſland</hi> nor from <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> it was in our Hearts to write this Epiſtle to Friends there, as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Dear Friends;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WE having this Oportunity, it was in our Hearts to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie our Loves in writing a few words unto you, by theſe our dear Friends, <hi>Katherine Norton</hi> and <hi>Eliz. Cater;</hi> and we would have gladly viſited you, if we could have gotten a Paſſage thither; for you have been often in our Remembrance, but in the Will of the Lord we ſtand, and in that Power that is unlimitted, where neither Earth nor Seas can ſeperate us from the Lord, nor one from another; but that is known which breathes for the Seed, and wreſtles with the Lord, as <hi>Jacob</hi> did. So <hi>dear Friends,</hi> to whom the Salutation of our Unfeigned Love reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, dwell at Home, keep in your Tents; <hi>for they that dwell at Home, they divide the Spoil, their Enemies ſhall become ſubject un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them.</hi> Truly, <hi>dear Friends,</hi> we ſhould have been glad to have ſeen your Faces, but in the Will of our Heavenly Father we ſtand; and we do believe, we ſhould have been comforted together; in the mean time, let us all be diligent to ſtir up one the other,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:31806:16"/>and to provoke one the other to Love and Good Works: So ſee that in Gods Vineyard ye may be all found, for they that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour there, they do receive their promiſe, which is an earneſt of that Inheritance that God hath prepared for all that love him. So dear Friends, there are but twelve Hours in the Day, in which we may all work; in the Night none can work; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid Chriſt Jeſus, who is the true Light, <hi>While ye have the Light, walk in the Light, that ye may be the Children of the Light, leſt Darkneſs come upon you.</hi> So dear Friends, in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned Love of our God (that can never be ſeperated, as we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide faithful) do we write unto you in that Love which firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got us unto God, and is as precious unto us as ever it was; yea, the deſire of our Hearts is, that in this feeling Life ye may all dwell, which is nearer then what can be declared either by Word or Writing: for bleſſed be the Lord God for evermore, this great and marvellous Light ſhines through Darkneſs, and ſhines in Peoples Hearts; and the Lord is working ſecretly, though they do little know it. And therefore, <hi>Friends,</hi> in the Holy Inviſible Power of the Immortal Living God, all dwell Low and Humble in that quiet and meek Spirit that thinks no evil, but in Lowlineſs of Mind eſteeming each other in the Lord, and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denying ſelf; ſo will you dwell upon the Rock Chriſt Jeſus, who is become our hiding-place, in this our Age and Generation, as he was in Ages paſt, unto whom we flee in time of Trouble, and we are ſaved; Everlaſting Holy Praiſes be unto his bleſſed Name for evermore: So in this weighty Power, Chriſt Jeſus, dwell Low, that you may ſpread at the Root as <hi>Lebanon,</hi> and bring forth Fruit upward, to the Praiſe and Glory of God, unto whom be Everlaſting Holy 'Praiſes forever, and for evermore.</p>
                  <p>So dearly beloved Friends, Brethren and Siſters, in the true Fellowſhip of the Goſpel, which is the Power of God unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, though this be the Day of <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Troubles, and the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> yet the Worm <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhall rejoyce, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall dwell ſafely; and the true <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> in whoſe Heart is found no Guile, the Seed Chriſt Jeſus, the Power of God, which doth and ſhall reign over all the Dark Powers of the Earth, who hath
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:31806:16"/>a Habitation in the Earth, which the Wo from the Lord is to. So in the Life and Power of God, and in this bleſſed Seed, which never ſinned, nor conſented to Sin, all dwell, that the Bleſſing of God eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one may receive, &amp; be kept in true Peace with the Lord, when Time ſhall be no more; for the Bleſſing of God is to the Seed; not unto Seeds many, but unto the <hi>one ſeed, Chriſt,</hi> that all may witneſs the Promiſe of God fulfilled, <hi>That the Seed of the Woman ſhall bruiſe the Serpents Head,</hi> in every particular where the Bleſſing is recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and where the Promiſe is Yea &amp; Amen forever; for <hi>Caleb</hi> &amp; <hi>Joſhua</hi> did enter into the Promiſed Land, who were of a right Spirit. So, dear <hi>Friends,</hi> keep your Dominion, and be true to your Teſtimony, that he may reign whoſe right it is; for the Devil, the Serpent, hath no right to reign in the Hearts of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but Chriſt Jeſus is come to deſtroy the Works of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and to reign in Righteouſneſs, and to ſet up his Government; and would have all People to come under his Government (for the Increaſe of his Government hath no End) that he may reign whoſe right it is: And here we can ſay, in the Truth of our Hearts, That the Son of God is come, and hath given us a good Underſtanding to underſtand and know the things of God; for the Light is broken forth, which comprehends all the Works of Darkneſs, and ſhines in the Hearts of the Righteous; and the Righteous do rejoyce in the Light, which gives the Knowledge of the Glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt. And ſo walk in the Light, and be encouraged, and you ſhall have the Light of Life; and ſtand faſt in your Liberty and Freedom wherein Chriſt Jeſus hath made you Free; and that none may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled with the Yoke of Bondage, which may cauſe the Juſt to ſuffer; <hi>For though Trouble and Sorrow may endure for a Night, yet Joy comes in the Morning;</hi> and ye ſhall come to ſing the Song of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Lamb.</p>
                  <p>So dearly Beloved <hi>Friends,</hi> be encouraged to keep to the Word of Patience, and the Lord God will keep you in the Day of Tryal, and in the Hour of Temptation; <hi>For the Rod of the Wicked will not alwayes lie on the Back of the Righteous; for the Wicked, and they that forget God</hi> (who Repent not) <hi>ſhall be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:31806:17"/>turned into Hell;</hi> Everlaſting Holy Praiſes be unto the Lord our God forever, and for evermore.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>From us your Friends, though unknown to you outwardly, yet well-known in the Myſtery of the Fellow ſhip,</signed>
                     <salute>the Power of God, in which we dearly Salute you all, and bid you all Farewel.</salute>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> 
                        <date>the 9th of the 12th Moneth, 1676.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> 
                        <date>the 4th of the 8th Moneth, <hi>1676.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <head>For the Friends of <hi>Road-Iſland.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>DEar Friends, in the openneſs of Gods bleſſed Life, in which our Unity ſtands, not only when we are together, but when we are ſeparated; in this is the Salutation of our dear Love unto you, for the Lord our God hath ſhed his Love abroad in our Hearts, in which love we can truly ſay, the Lord laid it upon us to viſit his Seed amongſt you, though we be the leaſt of many of the Lords People, and our Teſtimony is but little, yet we are ſure it is true for the Lord. So in the feeling of God's bleſſed Life, which cannot be limited, but limits all under it, and brings into true Subjection to do the Will of God: This bleſſed Life and Love of God, oh our dear Friends, which reaches over Sea and Land, this Love conſtrains us, as it did to viſit you, ſo to write unto you. Therefore, <hi>Friends,</hi> dwell together in Unity, and in this precious Love that thinks no Evil, nor is not eaſily provoked, but endureth all things; this Love ſeeketh not its own, but every one anothers good. <hi>Friends,</hi> we deſire you, That you would bear with us a little; for we do not write theſe things unto you becauſe ye know not the Truth, but becauſe you know it; and therefore a neceſſity is upon us to write unto you, That no Prejudices, nor Evil Surmiſings, nor Whiſperings, nor Back-bitings be or remain among you; for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:31806:17"/>theſe things work not the Righteouſneſs of God, but where ye lie in the bottom, though covered over with a Profeſſion of the Truth, yet ye will eat as a Canker: Therefore, <hi>Friends,</hi> we beſeech you to ſtand in Awe, and in the Fear and Dread of the Lord God, and ſin not; for we have known the Terrors of the Lord againſt Sin in our own Particulars, and alſo his Mercies, bleſſed be his Name forever and ever. And therefore, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you in the Love of God, that ye wait together to feel God's weighty Power, that ſo the ground Work ye may know, and the top Stone laid in the true Self-denyal, that ſo as Lambs of one Fold ye may feed together in the low Valleys; Everlaſting Glory and Honour be unto the Lord our God for all his Mercies, for they are exceeding great unto the Children of men in this Day of God's Salvation, which is now broken forth, and is large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifeſted; and the Voice of the Lord is heard, which Voice ſhakes the Earth terribly, and even removes it out of its place; and not only the Earth, but the Heaven alſo: And the Lord is gathering in both Profeſſors and Prophane; Everlaſting Bleſſing be to our God, the Work of the Lord proſpers: Therefore, <hi>Friends,</hi> that ye may all be diligent, and Helpers on of this great Work, as <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hurr,</hi> that ſo <hi>Miriam</hi>'s Curſe ye may eſcape.</p>
                  <p>So the Lord God Almighty, who ſeparated us from our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Country, and from our dear Relations, the Lord of Hoſts is his Name, he hath found us Worthy, with the reſt of his Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, to bear a Teſtimony unto his bleſſed Unchangeable Truth. Therefore, <hi>Friends,</hi> to the keeping of him who keeps his <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who neither ſlumbers nor ſleeps, we do commit the keeping of our Souls and Spirits, with yours alſo, who are of the Family of God; though we be far ſeperated, and cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the faces one of another, but in the Myſtery of the Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which is the Power of God, where the World knows us not, we bid you all <hi>Farewell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>From us your Friends, in the bleſſed Truth of God, in our meaſures,</hi> Thomas &amp; Alice Curwen.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:31806:18"/>
            <p>Friends here are generally well, and here is an increaſe daily; for a Prieſt comes to our Meetings, and People of all ſorts come, ſo that here is good Service for God, and the Truth increaſes; for the more the Enemy ſeeks to hinder the increaſe of Truth, the more it ſpreads: Therefore bleſſed will all they be, who abide faithful in the Truth. And we earneſtly deſire to hear from you in Writing; for our Dear Unfeigned Love is more than we can expreſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thù for Friends at</hi> Road-Iſland <hi>in</hi> New-England.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> the 11th of the 9th Moneth, <hi>1677.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>DEar Friends, <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Alice Curwen,</hi> whom I truly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the Lord; My Soul is truly comforted in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of you, and in the feeling of that Heavenly Life by which you are ſupported in God's Service amongſt us; my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit doth rejoyce and Praiſe the Lord our God in your behalf, who hath been very bountiful in viſiting of his Seed, by ſending of his faithful Servants and Miniſters amongſt us, to declare God's Way, which is Life, among whom ye ſhall be numbred. <hi>Dear Friends,</hi> this is a Salutation of my unfeigned Love and honourable Eſteem which lives in my Heart of you in the bleſſed Truth of God. And <hi>Dear Friends,</hi> I am not a little comforted, that ye have thought me worthy of a few Lines from you, which I have received; and do deſire, that ye may bteathe to the Lord our God for my Preſervation in the pure Truth, which is more to be deſired than all the World, and the Glory of it. And ſo, <hi>dear Friends,</hi> I ſhall conclude this with my dear Love in the Truth to you both, and remain</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Loving Friend in the Truth,</hi> John Readman.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:31806:18"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>An Epiſtle to <hi>Nathaniel Sylveſter</hi> and his <hi>Wife,</hi> at <hi>Shel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Iſland,</hi> the 6th of the 4th Moneth, <hi>1676.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>FRIENDS;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IF the Truth make us free, then are we free indeed: ſo let none grieve the Spirit of Truth, that the Power of the Lord may be felt, which keeps all in good Order, and brings the Mind into true ſubjection to do the Will of God, and not our own Wills; and therefore this is in our Hearts, as a Salutation of our Love, That you who are Parents may ſtand in the Truth of our God as Pillars, and watch over your Children in the Fear of the Lord, and keep them to Plainneſs of Speech, and not only you to them, and them to you, but to all people, that ſo the pure Croſs they may come to know, which is the Power of God, that it may rule the Mind, and this will bring them, as they ſtand and wait in the Simplicity of it, to ſee and put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all their Needleſs Attire, and ſo they will grow as tender Plants, and this is our Love in the Simplicity of our Hearts, that ye may ſtand over them in the Fear and Wiſdom of the Lord as Pillars; or elſe how will ye anſwer the Lord, who ſees the ſecrets of all Hearts? we do leave it to that of God in you to judge.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>THOMAS &amp; ALICE CURWEN.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>To Friends in <hi>Graveſend</hi> in <hi>Long Iſland.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>FRIENDS;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IN the Senſe of God's infinite Preſence and holy Power, in which our Life is preſerved, and in which our Unity ſtands with the Father and the Son, and one with another, do we ſalute you (as we abide faithful to the Lord) and in his bleſſed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:31806:19"/>Truth, a Meaſure whereof ye are Witneſſes of, and therefore it is in our Hearts, in remembrance of God's living Preſence, in which we were well refreſhed when we were together, and therefore to ſtir up your pure Minds, and to put you in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the bleſſed Preſence of the Lord; for ye are Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes how good the Lord is: Oh <hi>Dear Friends!</hi> the Lord even filled our Cup, and made it for to overflow, which broke our Hearts before the Lord, and one to another; yea, he even cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his living Preſence to be manifeſted amongſt us, to our great Satisfaction; Everlaſting Holy Praiſes be returned to his bleſſed Name forever and for evermore, for his Mercies are exceeding great. And now, <hi>Friends,</hi> in a living Senſe of the Lord's Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence do we write unto you, that ye may feel in reading hereof the Springings of that Life in which we write unto you, that ſo as Epiſtles in one anothers Hearts we may be read and known of all men. Oh, <hi>dear Friends!</hi> abide in the Vine Chriſt Jeſus, that ſo ye may bring forth precious Fruit to God, and this is a <hi>Chriſtian</hi>'s State indeed; for the Day of the Lord is come very near, and all that bear not this holy Fruit are nigh unto Curſing; Therefore do we dearly deſire, that you and all the reſt of our dear Friends, with whom we have been well refreſhed in God's bleſſed Truth, may ſo walk as to adorn the ſame, and be Poſſeſſors of it; that ſo they that fear not God ſeeing our Light ſhining, may confeſs that <hi>ye are of God.</hi> Oh Friends! ſee that your Lamps be trimmed, and that ye have Oyl in your Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels; for the Day of the Lord is near, when he will pour out his Wrath upon the <hi>Heathen</hi> that know him not, nor call not upon his Name in Righteouſneſs: and therefore, <hi>Friends,</hi> do we write unto you in a living Senſe, and in the Tenderneſs of our Spirits, that ye may be exerciſed in the Gift of God, every one in your ſeveral places; and none to hide the Lord's Money in the Earth, nor to account him a hard Maſter; for indeed he is exceeding good unto all that in the Simplicity of their Spirits ſeek after him, bleſſed be his Name forever and evermore. And if it be your Freedom, let Friends at <hi>New-York</hi> and at <hi>Fluſhen</hi> (as ye ſee convenient) ſee and read this Epiſtle in their Meeting; for our dear and unfeigned Love is unto you all more
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:31806:19"/>than we can here declare: And we cannot but return Praiſe and Thankſgiving unto the Lord, who raiſed his own Witneſs in you to receive our Teſtimony, though we be the leaſt of many of the Lord's People; and truly the Remembrance thereof is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding precious, bleſſed be the Name of our God forever and for evermore.</p>
                  <p>We are here waiting for our Paſſage to <hi>Barbadoes;</hi> and we deſire you, if you have a convenient Oportunity, to let us hear from you, and to write to <hi>Barbadoes;</hi> for it is our Joy, and the Joy of all that truly Fear the Lord, to hear from one another, and not only to hear, but to feel one another in the Life and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God's eternal Truth. So in the true Senſe of the Love of our God, wherein our true Comfort and Conſolation ſtands, we remain in the eternal Spirit of Truth, which hath made us free from the Law of Sin and Death; eternal Praiſes, Praiſes forever and for evermore be rendred and returned unto the Lord God of our Life, who is worthy forever and for evermore, <hi>Amen;</hi> in which we remain</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Friends in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchangeable Truth of our God,</hi> THOMAS &amp; ALICE CURWEN.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From</hi> Newport <hi>in</hi> Road-Iſland, <date>
                           <hi>the 9th of the 5th Moneth,</hi> 1676.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:31806:20"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>To Friends at <hi>New-York</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>FRIENDS;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IN that Love of our God which cauſed us to leave our Native Country, and all that was dear and near unto us, and come and viſit you, and in Obedience we came, and we are well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in the Lord, and refreſhed one in another, as you your ſelves very well know: and we wrote to you from <hi>Road-Iſland,</hi> and earneſtly deſired to hear from you to <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> which made us greatly to wonder that we did not receive one Line from you; we did expect to hear from you in writing by <hi>Lewes Morris;</hi> but indeed, we can truly ſay, <hi>That if our Exerciſe be great, yet the Lord is with us, who will not ſuffer us to be tryed but he alſo brings us through by the Arm of his holy Power:</hi> and ſo the Righteous can Rejoyce; Everlaſting Holy Praiſes be unto the Lord our God forever and for evermore. So that which is chiefly in our hearts at this time is, That we may all ſerve the Lord in Fear, and Rejoyce in Trembling; and with the Holy Man of God we can ſing of the Judgments of the Lord, and alſo of his Mercies; and ſo ſhall we all dwell together in the holy Fear low in our meaſures, where we offer up unto God a living Sacrifice well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing in his ſight. So mind our dear Love to Friends at the <hi>Graveſend,</hi> and <hi>Long-Iſland,</hi> and <hi>Oyſter-Bay;</hi> and let them know, that the Love of our God, which is ſhed abroad in our Hearts, reaches to the Seed, and breathes for the Preſervation of its Off-ſpring, that we may be comforted in our Travails concerning you; for we are very certain, that our Teſtimony is true for the Lord; for he rewards us an hundred fold into our Boſom; for we have had great Service in this Iſland, and the Lord hath given unto our two Talents two more, for which our Souls bleſs the Lord: Let all that feel his holy Power rejoyce
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:31806:20"/>with us, for the Work of the Lord goes on and Proſpers in this Iſland ſince our coming hither; he is turning back the Wiſdom of the Wiſe, though they laid many Baits and Snares for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, yet the Snares are broken, and we are delivered; and Truth proſpers over the Heads of them that do oppoſe; Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing holy Praiſes be unto the Lord our God, who carries his Lambs in his Arms, and proſpers his own Work: Here is a great openneſs in this Iſland, and the Lord is working ſecretly in Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Hearts, though they little know it who it is that ſmites them.</p>
                  <p>So dear <hi>Friends,</hi> when you have read this Epiſtle, which is a Salutation of our Unfeigned Love, you may read it in your Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; and let Friends at <hi>Graveſend, Long-Iſland</hi> and <hi>Oyſter-Bay</hi> ſee it, for you are all as one to us, whoſe Hearts are Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right to God. Our dear Love to <hi>Matthew Pryer</hi> and his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to <hi>Mary Willis</hi> and her Family, and <hi>Alice Crabe</hi> and her Family, and to <hi>John Dickſon</hi> and his Family, and to Friends about <hi>Fluſhen</hi> and <hi>Jamaco,</hi> to <hi>Hugh Couperwhete</hi> and his Wife; and though we cannot remember their Names, yet in that Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable Love that can never be forgotten, in which the Lord refreſht our Immortal Souls when we were together, do we dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſalute you all, and do bid you all Farewel. And if it be in any of your Hearts to write a few Lines to us, ye may write to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> for we ſhould be glad to hear from Friends at ſo great a diſtance, and how things are; but we do not know at preſent when we ſhall go Home; but in the Will of the Lord we ſtand, who hath given us good Succeſs, Holy Praiſes be to his Name for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever and evermore, ſaith your Friends,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From</hi> Oliver Hutton's <hi>at</hi> Barbadoes, <date>
                           <hi>the 12th of the 12th Mon.</hi> 1676.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Thomas &amp; Alice Curwen.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:31806:21"/>
            <p>There was a Widdow-Woman in <hi>Barbadoes</hi> that had <hi>Negro's</hi> to her Servants, who were convinced of God's Eternal Truth, and I hearing of them was moved to go to ſpeak to the Woman for their coming to our Meetings; and when I did ſpeak to her ſhe did deny me, and then I did write to her as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Martha Tavernor;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Cannot paſs by, but in Love write to thee, for in Love we came to viſit thee, and to invite thee and thy Family to the Meeting; but thou for thy part art like him that was invited to work in the Vineyard, and went not: And as for thy Servants, whom thou callſt thy <hi>Slaves,</hi> I tell thee plainly, thou haſt no right to reign over their Conſcience in Matters of Worſhip of the Living God; for thou thy ſelf confeſſedſt, that <hi>they had Souls to ſave as well as we:</hi> Therefore, for time to come let them have Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, leſt thou be called to give an Account to God for them, as well as for thy ſelf: So in thy old Age chuſe rather, as a good Man did, that both thou and thy whole Family may ſerve the Lord; for I am perſwaded, that if they whom thou call'ſt thy Slaves, be Upright-hearted to God, the Lord God Almighty will ſet them Free in a way that thou knoweſt not; for there is none ſet Free but in Chriſt Jeſus, for all other Freedom will prove but a Bondage,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>From thy Friend,</hi> Alice Curwen.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:31806:21"/>
            <p>Something in Anſwer to <hi>Thomas White</hi>'s Paper, which he did write againſt us, and not only againſt us, but againſt the whole Body of Friends, who did profeſs himſelf to be a Friend, but now joyns himſelf with the <hi>Ranters,</hi> who did come to our Meeting in <hi>New-Jarſey</hi> at <hi>Eliakim Wardall</hi>'s Houſe, who did give his Teſtimony for us in the Meeting, and ſaid, <hi>That we were ſent of God;</hi> and told us where he would have had us to have pointed another Meeting amongſt the <hi>Ranters</hi> in <hi>New-Jarſey,</hi> at a place called <hi>Midletown;</hi> &amp; he ſaid, <hi>He would come to our Meeting,</hi> and came not: We did write ſomething to him, and then he did write to us; and then we wrote an <hi>Anſwer,</hi> as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Thomas White;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>VVE cannot paſs by thee and thy muddy Stuff, but warn thee, becauſe we know the Terrors of the Lord in our ſelves againſt Sin, and alſo his Mercies, though we be the leaſt of many of the Lord's People, which thou calls our <hi>Tribe:</hi> And we finding thy Paper nothing worth, but for the Fire, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we write a few Lines unto thee to put thee in mind of thy own words in <hi>Eliakim Wardall</hi>'s Houſe, which was more large than we ſhall here declare; therefore call to mind, and do not eat thy own words, and ſay, thou was not refreſhed by T. C. &amp; A. C. We are Inſtruments in the hand of the Lord, and thou mayſt ſee thy own Folly and Madneſs, twiſting as the Serpent did; and if not by T. C. &amp; A. C. why did thou deſire of us to have a Meeting at <hi>Midletown?</hi> Thou dark <hi>Sodomite,</hi> out of thy own Mouth thou art judged and condemned with the Light of Chriſt Jeſus; for thou art turning backward from that of God in thy Conſcience, by which the Children of Light are led and guided into all Truth. And like a Serpent, thou art ſhooting out thy Venom and thy Sting, the Foyſon of Aſps is under thy Tongue: Thou mayſt read thy Condition, thou falſe Accuſer, for thou firſt deſiredſt a Meeting at <hi>Midletown,</hi> to ſee if the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:31806:22"/>Breaches can be made up, and then thou condemneſt us for mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting together, with many Lyes and falſe Accuſations, which was like the reſt of thy confuſed Stuff, forged up in thy Paper. And as for our viſiting of Friends in <hi>New-England,</hi> it is like the reſt of thy Accuſations; for we had been there before we did fee thy face: therefore let thy Mouth be ſtopt, and draw in thy Venom and Sting, and turn to the Light of God in thy Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and deal plainly and honeſtly with thy own Heart, that if it be poſſible, thou mayſt find Mercy with the Lord; for a Day of Blackneſs is over thee; <hi>for Rebellion is worſe than Witchcraft:</hi> And if thou findſt Mercy with the Lord, thou muſt paſs through the Fire, and the Sword thou muſt witneſs to cut down that which is exalted. So in the Plainneſs and Honeſty of our Hearts in the ſight of the Lord we have cleared our Conſciences, and remain.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Thy Friends, in the Truth of our God, which is out of all Imaginations,</hi> Thomas <hi>&amp;</hi> Alice Curwen.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From</hi> Jamaco <hi>in</hi> Long-Iſland <hi>in</hi> New-England, <date>
                           <hi>the 18th of the 3d Moneth,</hi> 1676.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>This for a Prieſt at <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> the 20th of the 11th Moneth, <hi>1676.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <hi>Friend,</hi> William Walker;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe Day of the Lord's Power is come, and the marvellous Light now ſhines, and the Lord is making his People a Willing People, according to his Promiſe; and the Call of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:31806:22"/>Lord is gone forth to call People out of Darkneſs into his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous Light; and the Trumpet of the Lord is Sounded and Sounding, that People may be awakened out of Sin and Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; ſo I being moved in the true Fear of the living God, and in his holy Power, which works ſecretly, the Day is come, bleſſed be the Lord God forever, that that which is revealed in ſecret muſt be declared openly, that ſo all may hear, that many may be turned from Darkneſs to Light, and from the Power of Satan to the Power of God; for I feeling a neceſſity to warn you of the Day of your Viſitation, thou for thy part beekened to a man to drive us away; but if I had not Freely Declared, as I Freely Received, Wo and Miſery would be my Portion; for the Search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of all Hearts is known, from whom none can be hid: And the Day haſtens that all Coverings ſhall be ſtript off, but the Spirit of the Lord; and therefore do I write unto thee, to mind the Day of thy Viſitation; for <hi>it is ſafe for every one to try all things, and hold faſt that which is good.</hi> So if it be in thy Heart to prove thy Practice by the Scriptures, as we are willing to prove ours, thou may come to Widow <hi>Wickame</hi>'s the next <hi>Sixth day,</hi> call'd by the men of thy Generation <hi>Friday,</hi> being the 20th of this Moneth; for we keep our Doors open, and drive none away by Force and Cruelty, but the deſire of our Hearts is to the Lord, That People may ſo hear, that they may know the thing that belongs to their Everlaſting Peace, before the Day of their Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation be over; <hi>For the Spirit of the Lord will not alwayes ſtrive.</hi> No more, but my Unfeigned Love to thee and all the Sons and Daughters of men; and the Deſire of my Heart is, That every one may know Chriſt, who is the Power of God unto Salvation: From me,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Thy Friend,</hi> Alice Curwen.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:31806:23"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>This was given forth to another Prieſt of <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> called <hi>Daniel Dikes,</hi> on the 8th of the 1ſt Moneth, <hi>1676.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <hi>Prieſt,</hi> Daniel Dikes;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IF thou hadſt been invited to a Feaſt, where thou mightſt have filled thy Belly, and have drunk Wine at thy pleaſure, and have had the chiefeſt Seat, and have been called of men <hi>Maſter,</hi> we do believe thou wouldſt have come; but thou art ſo far from being a Maſter, that thou art the <hi>Pariſh Servant,</hi> who hires thee, and thou receiveſt Wages of them; and therefore we tell thee plainly, that a mans Servant that is bought with his Money (whether black or white) is more honourable than thee; for in the inviſible Light thou art ſeen with the ſame Eye as <hi>Daniel</hi> in his Day ſaw the Prieſts, their Wives and Children, though they went in at the Privy Door: but now the Light is broken forth, bleſſed be the Lord God forever, and that every Boy and Girle that abides in the Light, which is inviſible, ſees your Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps: Therefore ſaith the Lord unto the Idol Shepherds, that feed not the Block of Chriſt, but their own Bellies, <hi>I will gather my Sheep, and they ſhall not alwayes he Meat for the Devourer, but I will feed them my ſelf, and they ſhall not need to ſay, Know the Lord and his Spirit, for ye ſhall all know me, ſaith the Lord, from the greateſt to the leaſt; for I will write my Law in their Hearts, and put my Fear in their inward Parts, ſaith the Lord God Almighty.</hi> Therefore, Oh Prieſt! I tell thee plainly, 'twas to a Feaſt that thou waſt invited; and the Lord is ſending out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the High-wayes and Hedges to call in all, and even to compell them that will not come, that ſo his Houſe may be filled, that ſo all may be leſt without excuſe, as he was that had not on his Wedding Garment, who was Speechleſs; for the Day is come, that that whcih is ſeen in ſecret muſt be declared openly: And therefore in the inviſible Light we are moved to write unto thee, ſeeing thee in the Light of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:31806:23"/>lighteth every man that cometh into the World, which hath long ſhined in Darkneſs, but now the commanding Power of the Lord is gone forth; and he hath commanded Light to ſhine out of Darkneſs, and it ſhines in Peoples Hearts, and will ſhine more and more untill the Perfect Day; for which a Remnant can bleſs the Lord, and ſing Praiſes to his Name, and unto the Lamb for evermore, who was ſlain from the Foundation of the World, but is now alive, and lives forever and evermore, and rules in the Hearts of the Upright: And therefore, in the inviſible Light, as I was waiting upon the Lord, my Heart was truly opened to write unto thee, ſeeing thee to be one of them that ſhut the Kingdom of Heaven againſt men, that will neither enter in themſelves, nor ſuffer others: Therefore ſaith Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Wo unto you, ye Whited Walls, ye Painted Sepulchres, ye Blind Guides;</hi> and indeed you are ſo, <hi>and lead the Blind, and a Pit of Darkneſs is before you:</hi> Therefore is our Advice unto thee, and to all whom it may concern, That ye turn to this inviſible Light, and as you wait in it, and abide with it, it will preſerve your Hearts and Minds to God, and ye ſhall not fall into the Pit. And if thou enquire of us, <hi>What is our Way?</hi> We tell thee plainly, Chriſt Jeſus, the Light of the World, who ſaid, <hi>I am the Way, the Truth and the Life; he that believeth in me, out of his Belly ſhall flow Rivers of Living Water:</hi> And He, even Chriſt Ieſus, the Power of God is the <hi>Original,</hi> and not <hi>Hebrew, Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin,</hi> which the <hi>Jews</hi> ſet over his Head when they Crucified him, as it is in theſe dayes; and as is ſaid before, he is our Way, and he is the Hope of our Glory; and we are not aſhamed to confeſs him before men; for if we ſhould not confeſs him before men, but be aſhamed of him, as too too many are, then he will not confeſs us before his Father in Heaven: Therefore, Oh Prieſt! we warn thee, that thou ceaſe giving thy Meanings to the Scriptures: Thou mayſt read thy Doom, in the <hi>Revelations; He that Adds or Diminiſhes, God will add unto him the Plagues written in that Book.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>THOMAS &amp; ALICE CURWEN.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:31806:24"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>An Epiſtle written to Friends at <hi>Thickets</hi> and <hi>Clifts</hi> Meetings at <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> the 20th of the 1ſt Moneth, <hi>1676.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TO you, <hi>Friends,</hi> of the <hi>Thickets</hi> and <hi>Clifts</hi> Meetings, and to all whom it may concern, in the Love of God that truly opens our Hearts, do we write unto you, to ſtir up the pure Mind, and to raiſe up that Love that brought us unto you, even the Love of God that firſt begat us by the Word of his Power, that we ſhould be as the firſt Fruits unto God; and this makes us to Cry many a time in the ſecret of our Hearts, both in Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and out of Meetings; <hi>Oh! how great is thy Loving kindneſs, O Lord! Oh, that the World knew it!</hi> And in the feeling of it we can truly ſay as one did, <hi>Oh! that all the Lord's People were Prophets, that they might ſpeak one by one, that all might be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted; and that the Lord would enlarge</hi> Japhet <hi>to dwell in the Tents of Shem;</hi> then there would be no complaining for want of Power, but the Lord would open even the Windows of Heaven, and pour out Bleſſings upon you, that ye ſhall not have room to hold it in, but the Overflowings of it you would feel in your own particulars; and when you were thus filled, you would bleſs the Lord, &amp; you would cry unto others to come away &amp; taſte &amp; feel how good the Lord is, for his Mercies endure forever to them that fear him and wait upon him. And therefore, <hi>Friends,</hi> we beſeech you think it not hard to keep your Meetings apart, for the Bleſſing of the Lord is as truly witneſſed in Meetings apart, both in Men and Womens Meetings; and though Women be the Weaker, yet he hath laid Help upon one that is Mighty, Oh! Praiſes, Praiſes, ſaith our Souls forever &amp; for evermore, who feel his Power in our Hearts at this time: And therefore do we write unto all that may be concerned in it, That ye beware of that Spirit that was in the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the days of old; for the Lord knows right well, before whom we ſtand, who knows the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:31806:24"/>of our Hearts and Spirits, that we judge no mans Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nor hint at no Particular, the Lord knows; but we have heard ſome ſay, <hi>That it was well in the Beginning, when there was not ſo many Meetings;</hi> and we ſay the ſame: But <hi>Friends,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, we beſeech you all, for our Spirits are bowed down in a Sence of the Work of the Lord in this Iſland; and therefore, ye that have known good dayes in your Infancy, reſt not there, but come to your Growth, to a Young mans ſtate, and to an Old mans ſtate; for according to the manner of men, in Twenty Years time we come to our Growth; much more in the Work of the Lord can we come to teach others: And therefore look not back, as the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did, who fainted in their Minds becauſe of their long Travel; but take heed of that Spirit that would not have many Meetings, nor to have Truth to ſpread; for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy lies near that would betray the Simplicity: Therefore thus ſaith the Lord in our Hearts this day, as he did unto <hi>Moſes</hi> in dayes paſt, <hi>Speak unto the Children of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>that they go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward;</hi> for this is the Day of the Lord's Appearance ſpiritually; he is bringing out of <hi>Aegypt</hi> by a ſtrong Arm; and bleſſed is every one that helps on the Work, and puts his Shoulder to it. So faint not, <hi>Friends,</hi> in your Minds, nor be not weary, for the Work is the Lords, and he will carry it on; it ſhall Proſper; and God proſpers it in this Iſland, Everlaſting Praiſes be unto the Lord our God, can our Souls truly ſay, who feel the Work of the Lord to Proſper: and therefore we ſay again, Let none faint in the Day of Tryal; for that's a Teſtimony that their Strength is ſmall: And therefore, <hi>Friends,</hi> be Bold and Valiant for God's bleſſed Truth, and take no thought, but wait upon the Lord; and if ye be called before Magiſtrates, the Lord will put a word into your Mouthes that they ſhall not be able to gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay: And if it be ſo that ye ſuffer joyfully the Spoiling of your Goods, ye ſhall come to witneſs, That the Earth is the Lord's and the Fulneſs of it; and they that Fear the Lord ſhall want no no good thing, neither for Soul nor Body: And if it be ſo, that the Devil caſt into Priſon, fear it not, but in Patience poſſeſs your Souls, for the Lord will bring thorow; for we ſpeak what we know; for the Lord has delivered us out of Priſon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:31806:25"/>and outwardly, and his Preſence has been with us in all our Troubles; and he has made us to ſing in Priſon, and in the Stocks, Praiſes be to the Lord God, and to the Lamb forever, ſayour Souls: But <hi>Friends,</hi> we do not write this to make our Sufferings known, but to encourage all to abide patiently, that ye may come through as Gold purified; for the Wicked are but like Waters, and their Perſecution is but like a Wave of the Sea; and though they riſe never ſo high, yet it is our Faith in God, That he that hath put a Limit to the Bound of the Sea, and hath ſaid unto it, <hi>Thus far ſhalt thou paſs, and no further, and there ſhalt thou ſtay thy proud Waves:</hi> Oh <hi>Friends!</hi> bleſs the Lord with us; for it is a Day of fulfilling. Therefore, O let Truth ſpread in every Particular; let it take Root downward and grow upward, and bring forth Fruit to the Praiſe and Glory of our heavenly Father. And this we have to ſay, That every Plant that he hath not planted, ſhall be pluck't up; and every Plant that his right hand hath planted, he watereth it, that it may bring forth more Fruit; and in this is our heavenly Father Glorified and Well-pleaſed, that we bear much Fruit; Everlaſting Praiſes be unto the Lord our God forever and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. So with our Unfeigned Love, we take leave of you, and remain</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Friends in that which never alters, nor never changes, but remains forever, do we Salute you all, and bid you all Farewel.</hi> Thomas &amp; Alice Curwen.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:31806:25"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>For the Mayor of <hi>Plymouth</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <hi>Friend,</hi> Richard Tomes;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>VVE do read in the Scriptures of Truth, that in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles dayes there was a noble <hi>Feſtus</hi> amongſt the Magiſtrates: Therefore do I write unto thee, that thou be not ſtired up againſt a peaceable People that meets together ſinglely to worſhip God in Spirit &amp; in Truth; for God is a Spirit, and will be worſhipped in Spirit &amp; in Truth; and until People turn to the <hi>Spirit of Truth,</hi> which is the Light within, with which he hath ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted every one that comes into the World; and he that hates this Light has it, and though they may kick againſt it, yet it ſtands a faithful Witneſs for God; and whatever People may profeſs, they never worſhip the living God acceptably; for we know at this day, that God hears not Sinners, no more then he did in the dayes of Old; and that the Prayers of the Wicked are abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to him, as well in this day as in times paſt; but he that fears God and doth his Will, them he hears; and the Will of God is done in hearing and obeying the Light; and by this did they witneſs, in dayes paſt their Hearts to be Sanctified, and this is it that we meet together for; and we are but yet learning the Lord's Prayer; and as we are willing to wait that the Will of God may be done in Earth, as well as in Heaven, the Lord has bleſt us, and we ſhall ſpread over the face of the Earth; and though <hi>Balaam</hi> and <hi>Balack</hi> would riſe up to Curſe <hi>Iſrael</hi> at this day, yet this Teſtimony is in my Heart for God, That he hath bleſt us, and no man can Curſe that which God hath bleſt: And as we keep the Word of his Patience, the Lord God will keep us in the Day of Tryal, which ſhall certainly come upon all that dwell on the Earth, and know not a Habitation in the God of <hi>Jacob;</hi> for the Day is come which many would have ſeen (wherein the Lord is bringing mighty Things to paſs, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veals his Secrets to them that truly fear him) the ſame which was in the Apoſtles dayes, wherein the Everlaſting Goſpel was preached, which is the Power of God unto Salvation; and if
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:31806:26"/>any preach any other Goſpel, let them be accurſed: And this Goſpel is a wonder to you, and is hid from you; and therefore ye periſh in your Sins, which ſeparate you from the Living God, and doth hinder good things from you, who live in the pleaſure of the Fleſh, and drink up Iniquity as the Ox drinks Water; but now in the Latter Dayes the Lord is pouring forth his Spirit upon all Fleſh, his Sons and upon his Daughters; and they do Preach and Prophecy in his Name, and in his Name do wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful things; and it is a great Wonder to all the World, who lies in Wickedneſs; and therefore the People periſh for want of Knowledge; for the Lord would have gathered you in this Day, as he would have gathered <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in the dayes of old, but they would not be gathered, and therefore they were left Deſolate: and the ſame is coming upon you, if you do not ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily Repent; for <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was deſtroyed, who would not be gathered, and then Lamentation, Wo and Miſery did fall upon them, and remains upon them till this Day; but the Lord hath gathered a Remnant into Covenant with himſelf, wherein <hi>Jacob</hi> doth rejoyce, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> doth dwell ſafely: And therefore the Sons of <hi>Jacob</hi> are not conſumed, though many be <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Troubles, and the Afflictions of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> which is now, as was in the Dayes of old; and they that ſuffer for him, they ſhall reign with him forever and for evermore, and fit at his right Hand in his Throne of Grace, and in his Kingdom of Glory forever and for evermore, where we ſhall Sing and Rejoyce with the Lord God and the Lamb forever; the Lamb that was ſlain in us in <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Aegypt,</hi> while the World had a Foundation in us, who was dead, but is now alive, whoſe Name is called the <hi>Word of God,</hi> which was in the Beginning, as the Scripture doth declare, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:31806:26"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>This was for the Prieſt of <hi>Ives, Joſhua Herning,</hi> the 19th of the 10th Moneth, <hi>1677.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I could not be clear in the ſight of the Lord, untill I had written a few Lines unto thee, ſeeing thee come into our Meeting with the Conſtable and his great Staff; and I heard thee ſay, That <hi>thou waſt an Informer;</hi> &amp; I tell thee plainly it were better for thee to be a Hang-man; for they do but execute others that by their Law are condemned to dye; but many Informers have brought ſhameful Death upon themſelves, and Ruin upon their Families, as it is on Record: Indeed, we confeſs we are a <hi>Suffering People</hi> at this day, as they were that went before us, who took joyfully the ſpoiling of their Goods, who were ſcoffed and mocked at, and ſaid, That Bonds and Impriſonments were their portion, and it was for their Teſtimony which they held, as thou mayſt read at large in the Scriptures of Truth, who haſt nothing now againſt us but concerning the <hi>Law of our God,</hi> and there ye go about tocatch us, as they of Old did <hi>Daniel;</hi> but oh Prieſt! read what became of theſe Informers, and of thoſe that informed againſt the three Children, thou blind Guide, which Chriſt cryed, <hi>We</hi> againſt, and ſaid, <hi>They were whited Walls, and painted Sepulchres, and wore long Robes, and loved to be called of men Maſters, and that they loved the upper moſt Romes at Feaſts, and greetings in the Markets;</hi> and further he ſaid, that <hi>By your Fruits your are known;</hi> and ſo it is this day: <hi>Wo unto you,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>for ye lay heavy Burthens upon the People, and ye ſhut the Kingdom of Heaven againſt men, ye neither enter in your ſelves, nor ſuffer others:</hi> Therefore ſaith Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Wo unto you.</hi> And if thou ask, how I know theſe things? I tell thee plainly it is by the inviſible Light which ſhines in my Heart, which manifeſts all things, as it is written in the Scriptures of Truth; and this Light was in the beginning, &amp; will be when all viſible things ſhall have an end, to which thou ſhalt be turned to give account of all thy Deeds done in thy Body all thy Life time, and of all thy hard Speeches againſt the Servants of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:31806:27"/>living God; therefore turn to it, and let it ſearch thy Heart, and believe in it: for this is my living Teſtimony for God, that it will deceive no man, but it will bring the hidden things of <hi>Eſau</hi> to Light, and believing in it and obeying it, it will lead out of Sin: Therefore Repent, &amp; pray unto the Lord, that he take thee not away in the midſt of thy Sins, leſt thou go down into the Pit out of which there is no Redemption. And as for our Names and Place of abode, it is in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> in a little Village, call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Beaklife,</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Alldingham,</hi> where we were ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to Priſon by ſuch a proud Prieſt as thee, becauſe we could not bow in this our day, no more than they could do in dayes paſt, but the Lord ſhortned that Prieſts dayes; and we do witneſs Chriſts words fulfilled in this our day, where he ſaid, <hi>That it ſhould come to paſs that the Devil ſhould caſt ſome into Priſon:</hi> But bleſſed be the Lord, who has delivered us; and we are at this day and time free of all the Goals in the World: therefore do we warn thee that thou come not upon thy Neighbours in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a Fine for us, for we have to ſatisfie of our own, and according to the Act ye are to fetch it where we live, whoſe Names are here ſet down, <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Alice Curwen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that further We do declare what the Lord hath done for us in the inncency of our Hearts, we Bleſs and Praiſe the Lord: Oh my Soul bleſs thou the Lord, that has witneſſed that Scripture of Truth this day fulfilled in my Ears, where Chriſt Jeſus ſaid, That <hi>men ſhould ſpeak all manner of Evil againſt us for his Names ſake, and that falſly; Rejoyce,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>and be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in Heaven.</hi> Oh, <hi>Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Praiſes,</hi> ſaith my Soul, with many Thouſands more that God hath redeemed from Death to Life; And to his bleſſed Name be Everlaſting holy Praiſes, and that for evermore, ſaith a Friend in the Truth of God, though the leaſt of many;</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Who am known unto men by the Name of</hi> Alice Curwen.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Huntingdonſhire.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:31806:27"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>For the Prieſt at <hi>Godmancheſter,</hi> the 21ſt of the 11th Moneth, <hi>1677.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Friend,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YEſternight I ſpoke to thee, as thou paſſedſt by, &amp; thou wentſt away laughing, like the reſt of thy Brethren, making merry over God's Witneſs in thee, which is the Grace of God, which appears at this day as it did in the Apoſtles dayes; and unto all them that believe in it and obey it, it works the ſame effect; everlaſting Praiſes be ſounded out unto the Lord our God at this day for his bleſſed Appearance, ſaith my Soul, who is come the ſecond time without Sin to ſave them that believe; Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Holy Praiſes be ſounded out aloud, ſaith my Soul in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, unto the Lord for all his Mercies, and that for evermore. And truly Prieſt (for I do not know thee by any other Name) my Spirit is grieved when I do ſee any of you, or where-ever I do meet with you, that you ſhould take upon you the charge of Peoples Souls, and to teach them the Way of the Lord; and in all my Travels I find no men ſo light and airy as you Prieſts are, who wear your long Robes; and by Chriſt's words (as you may read in the Scriptures) and by the Spirit of Truth (which God hath manifeſted in my particular) do I ſee you to be them which Chriſt cryed Wo againſt: therefore is the Word of the Lord as a Sword in my Mouth againſt the Myſtery of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the Merchants of her alſo; for the Lambs War is begun, and as it is written in the Scripture of Truth, <hi>The Beaſt and the falſe Prophet makes War againſt the Lamb and his followers, but God ſhall take the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet alive, and caſt them into the Lake that burns with Fire and Brimſtone forever and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more; and the Lamb and the Saints ſhall get the Victory.</hi> And ſo my Soul bleſſes the Lord that I have lived to ſee this day, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Scriptures are fulfilled; for it is the Lords day: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:31806:28"/>I deſire thee in love to thy immortal Soul, to priſe the day of thy Viſitation; for I could not be clear till I had eaſed my Spirit, who am a Friend to thy Soul, and truly loves all Men and Women alſo with that Love that God hath loved me withal,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Who am known by my Name,</hi> Alice Curwen.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Huntingdonſhire.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <hi>My Dear Friends,</hi> Thomas <hi>&amp;</hi> Alice Curwen;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I With many more, are glad to hear of the Arrival of <hi>John Grove</hi> his Ship, and we hope you are all ſafe; you are often in my Mind, but more your Innocent Lives and Converſation amongſt us, which ſhewed clear alſo your great Labour of Love amongſt us, which will not be forgotten in the Hearts of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; and I hope will not go without its Reward. The Lord God of our Life preſerve us in theſe Times of Troubles, which are at this time amongſt us, of which I do believe you will have a full Account: I am ſtraitned for Time at preſent, ſo cannot enlarge; only my dear Love (with my Childrens) is to you both, deſiring, that we may be all kept in his bleſſed Fear to our Lives end. So my dear <hi>Friends,</hi> Farewel.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Barbadoes, <date>
                           <hi>the 7th of the 5th Mon.</hi> 1677.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Loving Friend,</hi> Elizabeth Griffin.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:31806:28"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <hi>Dearly Beloved,</hi> Thomas <hi>&amp;</hi> Alice Curwen.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YOur good wills towards me and my Wife when you were with us, we cannot forget: And truly, <hi>Friends,</hi> would you know where I am, and how far I am grown in the Truth of our God, I cannot well reſolve my ſelf, by reaſon of the groſs Darkneſs, and the Straitneſs of the Way: I ſeek Reſt, but I cannot find it: I ſeek my Beloved, but cannot find him: I am often amongſt thoſe with whom God is not well-pleaſed, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not yet overthrown amongſt thoſe that luſt after Evil Things, thoſe that tempted Chriſt, and thoſe that Murmured, though not yet, through the Riches of the Patience and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, not deſtroyed of the Deſtroyer: Sometimes I think I feel the Well ſpringing up, the Day of the Lord's burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to burn like an Oven, and the Leaven working and the Seed of the Kingdom no more the leaſt of all Seeds, the Grave opening, and the Dead ariſing at the Voice of the Son of God: And at other times as one that Dreamed, and meer Stranger in <hi>Iſrael, I am Hungry, I am Thurſty, I am hardly filled;</hi> yet I muſt needs acknowledge, that ſometimes I do meet with Manna; and bleſſed be the Shepherd of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> I ſometimes drink, and am reſreſhed at the Brook by the Way: I ſtill wait for the bleſſed Hope and the Glorious Appearance of the great God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt: I ſee that Patience muſt have its Perfect Work. that my Beloved muſt not be awakened until he pleaſe, and that Times and Seaſons are in the Father's Hand; and am a Witneſs for him, That he is Faithful, who hath promiſed, by what of his Promiſes I have already found to be Yea and Amen in Chriſt Jeſus: He doth not break the bruiſed Reed, nor quench the ſmoking Flax; on whom I do wait to bring forth Judgment into Victory, to kindle his Refiners Fire, to conſume the Droſs and take away the Tinn, and to anſwer &amp; to ſave ſo as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:31806:29"/>by Fire, that I may become a Veſſel meet for the Maſters Uſe. Oh, Travel for me! Help me forward with your Breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and that I fall not in the Wilderneſs.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>From me</hi> Henry Byrch, <hi>who was a</hi> Baptiſt-Teacher, <hi>but now, through the Mercy of the Lord, am come to be taught of the Lord, and in meaſure eſtabliſhed in the bleſſed Truth of our God, to the Praiſe, Glory and Honour of the Lord our God, who is God over all, Heaven and Earth, bleſſed for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever and for evermore,</hi> Amen, <hi>ſaith my Soul, and the Souls of the Righteous, whom God hath redeemed from Death to Life; to him alone be Glory forever and evermore.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>Barbadoes, <date>
                           <hi>the 9th of the 7th Moneth,</hi> 1677.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <hi>Dear Friends,</hi> Thomas <hi>&amp;</hi> Alice Curwen,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YOur Letter I received, and I was very glad to hear of your Well-fare, and of your arrival ſafely in <hi>England;</hi> and truly <hi>Friends,</hi> I know you cannot eaſily be forgotten by me, nor ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good Friends in this Iſland, for your faithful Service, Pains and Travel, whilſt among us, in the Service and Work of the Lord; and the Deſire of my Soul is, That we may be all kept in a living Senſe of his Holy Fear dwelling in our Hearts at all times; for the Fear of the Lord is only that that keeps the Heart clean, and preſerves us in the greateſt Tryals and Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes that we meet withal, that ſo continuing faithful to the end of our dayes, we may receive our Reward from our Heavenly Father, even the Salvation of our Immortal Souls. So dear <hi>Friends,</hi> I need not uſe many words unto you: I could not well omit ſending theſe two or three Lines, though at preſent ſomething ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>itned in point of time. Friends are generally in pretty good Condition, though of late we were like to have had a further
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:31806:29"/>Breach here amongſt us, by reaſon of altering Men and Womens Meetings, at the <hi>Bridge-Town;</hi> but bleſſed be the Lord, the Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings at preſent are pretty well ordered and compoſed, ſo that I am in good hopes that all Difference and Strife will ceaſe, and Truth will out-live all; here are good Friends, which I hope will keep down theſe Unruly Paſſions &amp; Heats that were uſual and too often accuſtomed by ſome to riſe amongſt us. My Wife deſires dearly to be remembred to you. So with my True and Unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Love to you both, I reſt and remain</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Friend and Brother, in my Meaſure of the bleſſed Truth,</hi> John Todd.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> 
                        <date>the 4th of the 11th Moneth, 1677.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <hi>Loving Friends, dear</hi> Thomas <hi>&amp;</hi> Alice;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WE do dearly ſalute you in the bleſſed Truth of our God; and in the ſence of the ſame do our Souls truly rejoyce, and our Hearts are made truly Glad, in that we feel one another in that bleſſed Life which keeps our Souls alive to God, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and aſſunder: And truly, our <hi>dear Friends,</hi> you have been often in our remembrance; and in the ſenſible feeling of that bleſſed Life hath our Souls been truly refreſhed in you; though many Miles aſſunder, yet can we truly ſay, That oft-times our Hearts and Souls have been truly refreſhed in you, and the Sence of that Living Teſtimony you left behind you, that oft-times lives in our Hearts: Oh! bleſſed be the Lord our God for evermore, that hath brought us to ſee this bleſſed Day, in that we can feel one another in this bleſſed Life, which keeps our Souls alive to God, and tender one to another: And ſo, our dear Friends, words are too ſhort to tell of the goodneſs of God to our Souls, as our Minds have been truly ſtaid on him: Oh! how hath his Love flown forth in our Hearts to the great
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:31806:30"/>Refreſhment and Satisfaction of our Immortal Souls, together and aſſunder! We have known the Renewings of the Bleſſings and Mercies of the Lord unto our Souls; Oh, praiſed be the Name of our God forever and for evermore, that he hath brought a Remnant to ſee this bleſſed Day of the flowings forth of his Love in our Hearts, which makes us truly to rejoyce more than the Encreaſe of any Viſible Thing. And ſo, our dear Friends, how have we known the bedewings of the Lord, as our Minds &amp; Hearts have been kept low before him; and in the ſence of the ſame we have been kept freſh and green, and alive to God; Oh! holy Praiſes be to the Name of the Lord our God forever &amp; for evermore. And ſo, our dear Friends, having not much more in our Hearts to you at this time, our dear Love is to you, with the reſt of Friends: We remain</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your dear Friends, Brother and Siſter, in that bleſſed Truth of our God,</hi> Stephen Richards, Anne Barber.</signed>
                     <dateline>Falmouth, <date>
                           <hi>the 1ſt of the 3d Mon.</hi> 1678.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <hi>Dear Friends,</hi> Thomas <hi>&amp;</hi> Alice Curwen;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>MY True Love dearly ſalutes you both, and all True-hearted Friends that may enquire after me: Since your coming away good Friends have been much wanting, and things have been pretty high againſt me; but I hope, in the general, it will not prevail, and the Lord hath made me willing to bear; but the Lord's hand of Power will preſerve the Simple and Upright in Heart, <hi>Amen,</hi> ſaith your Friend, in Brotherly Love,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Barbadoes, <date>
                           <hi>the 2d of the 6th Mon.</hi> 1677.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Ralph Freatwell.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:31806:30"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Dear Friends;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Could not be clear, without the Tender of my true Love unto you both, whoſe Labour of Love, Service and daily Travels for the Lord's Truth in this Place will never be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by a Remnant, and the Lord's Reward I know is with you; to whom belongs all Praiſe, Honour and Glory, both now and forever, and for evermore, <hi>Amen,</hi> ſaith your Friend,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thomas Freatwell.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <hi>Dear Friends,</hi> Thomas <hi>&amp;</hi> Alice Curwen;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IN the Unchangeable and Everlaſting Love of God, do I dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſalute you both: I have received a Letter from you, which was very acceptable to me; in the reading of which I was ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſolated and refreſhed; and your Love to us all I cannot, nor I hope ſhall not forget; Oh! the many precious Meetings and Opportunities which we enjoyed when ye were with us! the Remembrance of which was precious, but the glorious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God which we enjoyed was much more precious: Oh! the goodneſs of the Lord God is Unutterable, who continues his Love to us daily, and accompanies us with his living Preſence at all Times, and in all Places, as we abide low in his Fear, and are found faithful in his Work and Service: Oh! my Soul's Deſire is, That I may be kept low before him forever: And my <hi>Friends,</hi> I hope your Prayers to the Almighty will be for the ſame.</p>
                  <p>The Lord's Truth doth proſper mightily, and his Power is over this whole Iſland, though the Devil doth Rage in his Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments mightily, even at this preſent time, more than ever before, as I think; and ſuch Threatning Times againſt the poor Innocent Lambs, as have not been known; and only becauſe of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:31806:31"/>of God's bleſſed Truth in this little Iſland: But we fear not man, but are greatly encouraged to go on in the Work of the Lord, and be Valiant for God until Death; for I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded here is a little Remnant, whoſe Truſt is in the Lord, that doth not regard any of their Threatnings and Unrighteous Laws, which are lately made, if they were ten times greater than they are; and I believe We ſhall have the Victory, through the Power of the Lord, as we abide ſtedfaſt in the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable Truth of our God, though many that are not faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the Lord God, but let their Teſtimony fall, who are the fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and unbelieving, may loſe the Crown of Eternal Life: And your Love to our Family was very large, and I am right ſenſible of it, in the Sence of which I am refreſhed at this preſent; and ſo, in the ſame Love do I dearly ſalute you: And ſo with my Love to all Friends, I remain</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Loving Friend, in the Everlaſting Truth of God,</hi> Robert Thorp.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>An Epiſtle to <hi>Swarthmore</hi> Meeting.</head>
                  <p>DEar Friends at <hi>Swarthmore</hi> Meeting, to whem is my true Love; and I have an Honourable Eſteem in my Heart for you all, who keep to your firſt Love, and retain your Integrity to this day, which is a bleſſed Day indeed of the Breakings-forth of the bleſſed weighty Truth, which we breathed for in the dayes of our Infancy. Oh! what ſhall I ſay to ſtir up your pure Minds, that ye may travail forward, that none may ſtand ſtill, nor none may go backward! for this is the Day of God's ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Travel, God has made me a living Witneſs; and therefore my dear Friends, as one that has been nurſed up there, can I not at this time contain my ſelf, but in a living Senſe of the dayes paſt, when we waited together for true <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Hope: And Oh! how is my Spirit bowed down in the weighty Power of the bleſſed Appearance of the Breakings-forth of the weighty
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:31806:31"/>Truth in the dayes of our Infancy, in that Meeting which I ſo dearly love and truly honour in the Lord, though the breakings out at firſt of the Power of the Living God was very Dreadful and very Terrible, yet (oh my Friends!) I cannot but eaſe my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit a little at this time, being loaded with the Power of the Lord, which cauſes me to write. And oh! what ſhall I ſay of the bleſſed heavenly Melody, and the ſpiritual Songs, yea, the new Song that God hath put into our Mouthes; Oh! endleſs Praiſes, ſaith my Soul, with you my <hi>dear Friends,</hi> with whom I would be glad that I might ſit down with you once more, that we might ſing together of the Mercies of the Lord, and of his pure Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in this our day, as poor <hi>David</hi> did. And oh! how am I affected in my Bowels for an Opportunity that we might be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted together! but I do not ſee my Service over, that I may come to my Place of Abode in the oatward; for I can truly ſay, that I have not taken up another; and I am as a Weaned Child at this time: and the Deſire of my Heart to God is, <hi>That theſe few dayes I have to ſpend may be in his bleſſed Truth,</hi> which is more to me than all the World: therefore let none of you queſtion in your Minds my coming home; for when I have done the Will of God, who am one of the leaſt of the Lord's People, I ſhall be willing to come into the North, and ſit down with you, and wait upon the Lord, who hath brought me thus far towards my Native Being, and yet my way is ſhut up, that I cannot come Home. Oh my <hi>Dear Friends!</hi> breath with me to the Lord for the Proſperity of this great Work, which the Lord hath made me Inſtrumental in; though but weak and little, yet bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the Lord who appears ſtrong and weighty in every need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful time, though in weak Inſtruments; let his Name be purely Praiſed, and had in Everlaſting Reverence from Age to Age, and from Generation to Generation, ſaith my Soul, which is Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, and that for evermore. So, as I began in a Sence of the Love of God, and in his weighty Power, in that do I dearly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute you, and bid you all Farewel; and remain as one of God's Flock, and that Family where we were begotten to God, for which my Soul ſhall bleſs the Lord, whilſt I have a Day to live.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Huntingdon</hi>-ſhire, <date>the 29th of the 11th Moneth, 1677.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Alice Curwen.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:31806:32"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <hi>My Dear and Well-beloved Friends,</hi> Thomas <hi>&amp;</hi> Alice Curwen;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>MY dear Love is to you both; and by this you may know that we received your Letter from <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> the which indeed was very acceptable to us, and I was refreſhed thereby; I carried it to our General-Meeting at <hi>Oyſter-Bay,</hi> and it was read in the Men &amp; Womens Meeting; and I know many were truly glad to hear of your Well-fare, and the Proſperity of Truth. My <hi>Dear Friends,</hi> you are often in my remembrance, and the remembrance of your Savoury Life is very pleaſant unto me; for I am a Witneſs with you, That the Glory of the Lord often filled his Temple when we were together; and the Lord's Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Love is not wanting to his People that wait upon him in the Uprightneſs of their Hearts, for he openeth of his pure Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and refreſheth his own, though many are the Exerciſes of his People: We are, as it were, a Song among a wild Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and thoſe Ranting Spirits are much as they were when ye were here; they come in the like manner Ranting, Roaring, Singing and Dancing int our Meetings; &amp; it is the harder to bear becauſe it caſts ſtumbling-blocks in the way of the Simple; for ſome of the World think they are of us, and call them <hi>Quakers;</hi> ſaying, <hi>Look where they differ among themſelves!</hi> Theſe <hi>Ranters</hi> were very Wicked at <hi>Oyſter-Bay</hi> the laſt Meeting; when the Meeting was near ended my Husband was taken violent Sick with a Vomiting and Gripes; ſome of them hearing of it were very glad, and ſaid to me, <hi>I ſhould loſe my Right Eye and my Right Arm;</hi> and came near the Door where we were, and where my Husband lay ſick; and cryed, <hi>Wo, Wo, Wo to that Damned</hi> Story <hi>and</hi> Jezebel <hi>his Wife.</hi> Friends are prety well over their Spirits in theſe Parts, and generally well at <hi>Craveſend, Oyſter-Bay</hi> and <hi>Weſtcheſter;</hi> there is much Affiction on <hi>Joſiah Parnel,</hi> his Family hath been much afflicted with Sickneſs. My <hi>dear Friends,</hi> I am glad to write to you now, not knowing when I may have the like time again, I being with Child, and wanting but about ſix Weeks of my Account. My dear Husband's dear Love
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:31806:32"/>is to you both. So not knowing how the Lord may be pleaſed to deal with me, I dearly ſalute you, and take my leave of you both, in that Love which is of the Lords begetting.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your True Friend,</hi> Patience Story.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>New-York</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> 
                        <date>the 10th of the 8th Moneth, 1675.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Salem</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> the 22d of the 5th Moneth, <hi>1677.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Dear and Well-beloved Friends;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IN the Bleſſed Everlaſting Truth of our God, revealed and made manifeſt, do I at this time dearly ſalute you. My dearly Beloved in the Lord, unto whom the Salutation of my Love abounds, and with whom I have been well refreſhed in that pure and heavenly Unity, which makes us near unto the Lord, and one to another, even in that endleſs love which cannot be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, &amp; which nothing can ſeparate from, but it reacheth over Sea &amp; Land, for it is unlimited, neither can any Waters quench it: Oh! read me here and feel me here, even in that which Tongue cannot expreſs, nor Lips declare; for truly in this are you dear and near unto me; for as the Truth is dear and precious unto me, ſo are they that dwell in it, even in this bleſſed Truth which the Lord God hath been pleaſed to make a Remnant partakers of in this our Day and Age, and hath cauſed us with them to taſte of his heavenly divine Love, which floweth from the Fountain of End<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Life, in which we can feel one another, and truly rejoyce tegether in the Spirit, though ſeparated in the outward, and may not ſee one anothers faces any more in the Fleſh; yet as we dwell in that which is Immortal, we ſhall enjoy one another in the Inviſible Life, which changeth not, where there is Joy and Pleaſure for evermore: Oh! bleſſed and magnified be the Name of our God forever, who is not wanting unto them that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:31806:33"/>put their Truſt in him, but he ſupports and preſerves in all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and Tryals whatſoever. And dear Friends, for ſo you are to me in the Truth, that changeth not: for you are as an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle written in my Heart never to be blotted out, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of you is a refreſhing to me, when I call to mind the bleſſed Society and Fellowſhip we enjoyed when we were to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, in which the Lord God of Heaven preſerve and keep us forever unto the end of our dayes, ſo ſhall we reap a good Harveſt, if we faint not, and come to lay down our Heads in Peace and be at reſt with the Lord when Time ſhall be no more. Dear Hearts, I have much to write unto you, but being in haſte time will not permit, I being alſo but ill in Body. I am willing to give you an Account concerning <hi>Margaret Brewſter,</hi> whom you know, who came lately from <hi>Barbadoes</hi> in the Lord's Service to <hi>Boſton,</hi> where ſhe performed it, I being alſo with her in her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and in her Sufferings (except Whipping) as alſo was <hi>Lydia Wright</hi> and <hi>Barbary Bowers,</hi> and <hi>John Eſton</hi>'s Son alſo a Priſoner with us a Moneth. And Dear Hearts, I have met with many Tryals ſince I ſaw your Faces, but the Lord hath hitherto pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved me through it all, bleſſed be his Name forever. I cannot now give you an account concerning my Mother and Brothers, who were taken Captives by the Cruel <hi>Indians</hi> ſome Moneths; but the Lord hath delivered them, and they are here now with me. So <hi>dear Friends,</hi> being in great Haſte, I muſt take my leave of you, committing you to the Care and Keeping of the Lord, in which Everlaſting Love I bid you Farewel, my dear Friends Farewel, who am</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your True and Real Friend, Mary Milles.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Friends here in general their Love is to you. I received your Letter with Gladneſs of Heart, and deſire to hear from you again.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:31806:33"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>From <hi>Fluſhen</hi> in <hi>Long-Iſland</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> the 15th of the 7th Moneth, <hi>1677.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <hi>Dear and Inwardly beloved Friends,</hi> Thomas <hi>&amp;</hi> Alice Curwen;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YOu are both dear and near unto me, as my own Life; for I can truly ſay, that I have been often Refreſhed in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of you, feeling you in that dear Love and Life which proceeds from him who is our Life, and length of our dayes, in whom we live and have our Being, who is our Strength in time of need, when Tryals come and Exerciſes come, we find him a God at hand, and not afar off, bleſſed and praiſed be his holy Name forever, ſaith my Soul, for his unſpeakable Love, by which he hath gathered us near unto himſelf, and near one to another, by the Arm of his endleſs Power, which reaches over Sea and Land, and reaches to his own, wherein we have true Fellowſhip one with another in the Spirit of Truth, where the World knows us not; for therein doth his Worſhip ſtand, and ſuch doth the Lord ſeek to worſhip him, that worſhip him in the Spirit and in the Truth, bleſſed be his holy Name, who is God over all, bleſſed be his holy Name forever and for evermore, who hath filled our Hearts with his living Preſence, which doth engage us more and more to follow him, and to lean upon him; for his Judgments are pure, and he delights to abound in Mercy. And ſo in that Everlaſting Love, which our Heavenly Father hath loved us from the beginning, I do dearly ſalute you both; for you have often been in my Remembrance ſince we have been ſeperated as outwardly, and have been often with you in that bleſſed Truth wherein our Unity ſtands, which endures forever, which will live over all, and out-laſt all the invented Worſhips which the Devil hath begot many into; but their Day is almoſt over; for they are all in Confuſion, and all in Heaps; but bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the holy and ſacred Name of the Lord forever, who has preſerved a Remnant to ſtand in their Teſtimony for the Honour
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:31806:34"/>of his Everlaſting Truth. <hi>Friends</hi> are generally well in Health, bleſſed be the Name of the Lord forever and for evermore. So having this opportunity I was willing to write theſe few Lines. <hi>Friends,</hi> you are dear and near unto me, and the Springs of Love and Life do often flow ſorth unto you more than Tongue or Pen can expreſs. So no more but</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your aſſured Friend and Brother in the Truth of our God,</hi> Matthew Pryar.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>And as Opportunity preſents let me hear from you. Friends have ſuffered pretty much at <hi>Boſton</hi> ſince you were there; <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet Brewſter</hi> of <hi>Barbadoes</hi> hath been ſorely Whipt, and many Friends more; and here are a great many Friends come over to <hi>Delaware,</hi> and I fear that there is great need of Faithful Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers in theſe parts. No more, but my dear Love to you both.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Matthew Pryar.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Dear Friends, <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Alice Curwen;</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IN that Love of God which is Everlaſting and Endleſs in all his dear Babes and Children, whom he hath begotten by his Immortal Word, do I ſalute you, and you are often in my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, although far ſeperated as to the Outward, yet near in that which is Inviſible and Immortal, in the Life of Innocency, in which Life you were made inſtrumental in the Hand of our God to comfort me and hold me up in a living hope, when I was well nigh overwhelmed with Sorrow; but Praiſes are given by me unto our God that lives forever, who hath given me Patience to wait his time, and a Contented Heart, that into what Eſtate and Condition I may be brought, I hope I ſhall be contented.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:31806:34"/>
                     <hi>Dear Friends,</hi> I do own dearly your Labour of Love, and in the ſenſe of the ſame do bid you Farewel;</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Who am your Friend in the Truth Francis Colley.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Fluſhen</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> 
                        <date>the 15th of the 8th Moneth, 1677.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>DEar and Well-beloved Friends, <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Alice Curwen'</hi> whom I love in the Truth; and as my Love was dear to you when you were with us, ſo it remains now when we are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated, and my Heart is truly knit unto you in Unfeigned Love; and as you were a Comfort and a Strengthning in my great Weakneſs when you were with me, which I cannot forget, though far ſeperated; but I do ſay, <hi>The Lord reward your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of Love into your Boſoms;</hi> for the Lord hath of his abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant Love raiſed me from a weak eſtate, that I may yet remain in the Land of the Living, to declare his Praiſe, and to ſignifie my endeared Love to my Brethren and Siſters, and to bear a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Teſtimony for my God againſt the Wrong Spirits, that bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the Seed of God. So my <hi>dear Friends,</hi> I have not much to acquaint you with, only that which was fore-ſeen, <hi>That Bad Spirits are working their own Deſtruction.</hi> So in that Love which I began, I do take my leave, and remain</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Friend and Siſter, Mary Tyllton.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Graveſend</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> 
                        <date>the 15th Day of the 8th Moneth, 1677.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:31806:35"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Antego,</hi> the 19th of the 4th Moneth, 1677.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Dear Friends, <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Alice Curwen;</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>MY true love is to you both, deſiring your Everlaſting Well-fare and Well-being in God's Everlaſting Truth, that is broken forth amongſt us, bleſſed be his Name forever, who does daily engage us with his Love, and gives us a living Experience of his Mercies and Goodneſs, who feeds our Immortal Souls, and keeps us freſh and green, and bears up our Heads in the time of great and deep Exerciſes and Tryals, which we do meet withal; Everlaſting Praiſes and Glory be to his Name forever: ſo that we can ſay of a Truth, <hi>Good is the Lord to all that wait upon him, and chuſe him to be their chiefeſt Beloved;</hi> who indeed is the chiefeſt of Ten Thouſand to his little Remnant, that has none in Heaven but only the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, nor none on Earth in compariſon of him. And ſo deſiring we may forever wait in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleneſs upon the Lord, that he may keep us and preſerve us in the ſenſe of his Love, breathing and crying unto the Lord one for another in the bleſſed Seed and Gift and holy Spirit, that the Lord hath bleſſed through all Ages and Generations; Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Praiſes be unto his holy Name forever. Oh Friends! your Faithfulneſs the Lord hath made me in my meaſure ſenſible of, wherein my Soul is comforted, being Members of the one Body, of which Chriſt Jeſus is the Head and Leader, that goes before his People, and leads into the green Paſtures of Life, which the World cannot give us, nor take from us.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>JASPER TREGOUSE.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:31806:35"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Dear Friends, <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Alice Curwen;</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Received your Lines and your Friend <hi>R. J.</hi> and cannot but accept kindly of your Remembrance of me in the Lord, and was refreſhed in them, and your true Love therein, as I have alſo been in your Company in ſeveral good Meetings by God's Power refreſhed, for which let him have the Praiſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever: and your tender and dear Advice in the Truth is owned, and I deſire your Remembrance of me in the Lord may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, and that I may be preſerved through all Tryals to God's Praiſe, and worthy of his Mercies and Loving-kindneſs, which is large and incomparable. And, <hi>dear Friends;</hi> your Labour of Love in, and Service for the Lord, is not to be ſlipt out of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance in many Hearts in this Iſland, but is ſtill very freſh and green; and your Reward (I queſtion not) is in your Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, and will be with the Lord, who was and is the exceeding great Reward of his Servants both in others and in this Age, who were willing to forſake their Country and Kindred at his Requirings. So <hi>dear Friends,</hi> in the Salutation of that Love which exceeds all other I remember you, and deſire to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred by you. And if you ſee <hi>G. F.</hi> mind me to him; I have him in due Reſpect and Honour, though I am as one of the leaſt of the Thouſands of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yet of true <hi>Jacob</hi>'s ſtock, the Stem is felt through the Goodneſs of <hi>Jacob</hi>'s God, whoſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is better than this World's Glory.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Friend and Brother in meaſure of God's Power, <hi>JOHN BARKER.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> 
                        <date>the 1ſt of the 5th Moneth, 1676.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:31806:36"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Dear <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Alice Curwen;</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>TO whom is my dear Love, deſiring theſe precious Seaſons may never be forgotten, wherein we have been ſweetly watered and refreſhed together, but that the Glory of all may return to him in whom all our freſh Springs are. Your Service for God amongſt us I believe will be owned forever, and a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony thereof is freſh in the Hearts of a Remnant in this Iſland; and a ſad and bitter Condition are many reduced to who oppoſed your Teſtimonies, and ſo have come to wither and blaſt, as is wofully manifeſt by <hi>Henry Jones</hi> at this preſent, who is gone out of the Unity into the Enmity, and heaped up a parcel of dirty ſtuff in writing againſt Friends, and ſome others there: about ſtand by him, I think none but ſuch as are out of the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of meeting with their Families: I write the leſs of theſe things, becauſe I believe <hi>William Mullnex</hi> may give you a fuller account.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dear Friends,</hi> your honourable Service and innocent Behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our amongſt us cannot be forgotten by a Remnant in this Iſland, who would be glad (if the Lord ſaw meet) once more to ſee you; but in the mean time, I deſire we may be bound up toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in that one Spirit which partakes of the Dew from Heaven, and keeps alwayes green and freſh, bloſſoming and bringing forth Fruit well-pleaſing to the Lord. And the Deſire of my Heart is, that in your Breathings to the Lord, I may not be forgotten, who love and honour in my Soul all true-hearted and right-begotten Friends, who have the right Image, yea, the Father's Image ſtamped upon them, and with ſuch I hope to be one for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. So no more at preſent, but mine with my Wife's dear Love to you both, I remain</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Friend in the neareſt Relation,</hi> Edward Wright.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> 
                        <date>the 18th of the 12th Moneth, 1679.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:31806:36"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Dear Friends, <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Alice Curwen;</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>MY dear and well-beloved Friends in God, who hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten us to himſelf in his bleſſed Truth, and ſo one to another, in which my Soul and Spirit doth ſalute you both: Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtill in my Heart your faithful Labour and Courage in which you travailed amongſt us here, to the refreſhing of the Honeſt-hearted, and lives freſh in the Hearts of the Upright. Oh! how did the Lord make you as a Nurſing-Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the tender weak Lambs of God! and laboured to gather in the ſtraying Sheep, which were wandring from the Flock, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to bring them into the Fold again, where Reſt is truly known: for in the Out-goings and Wandrings there is a Spirit that is ſeeking for Liberty, but not that of God, but that which will not bow to Chriſt's Yoke; in which your Spirits had a ſore travel whilſt here amongſt us, and all the Valiant to this day do feel the ſame; yet as we keep to the Lord, we do find Victory over all the Contrary Oppoſing Spirits, and the Lord's Power and Living Preſence is with us to our great Refreſhings, and Spiritual Comfort of the little ones, who keep low in his Fear, and are made willing to follow him through whatſoever he will carry them; ſo that we can ſay, <hi>It is very good to keep near to the Lord, that we may feel him to bear us up continually, in Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, Troubles and Afflictions,</hi> in which we are made to Rejoyce more than in the Increaſe of Corn, Wine or Oyl, to God's Praiſe and Glory, and to the Comfort of our Souls, and to the carrying on of his great Work which he hath begun, and will carry on by his Faithful, Upright, Single-hearted Ones. The Lord raiſe up more Faithful Ones, that may ſtand up for God, and plead God's Cauſe againſt all that ſhall oppoſe it, as he did faithful <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Joſhua</hi> in the day of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, that like the good Spies, may give a good Report of the good Land, and ſo encourage, but not diſcourage any, but are willing to help forward the hindmoſt of the Flock, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:31806:37"/>the foremoſt, ſo that we may all come to travel on to the Land of Reſt, that we may all come to praiſe God toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with one Heart and one Mind, and bleſs him together for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, ſaith my Soul.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> 
                        <date>the 12th of the 3d Moneth, 1676.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Elizabeth Gretton.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>THE People of God called <hi>Quakers</hi> being met together in the Fear of the Lord to worſhip God, and to feel the Preſence of the Lord, whereby we might ſtrengthen and edifie one another, to the Praiſe and Glory of our God, who is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy forever; and after we had been ſome hours in the Meeting, there came in a Conſtable, called, Conſtable <hi>Noyſe,</hi> and a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, called, <hi>Benjamin Gibs,</hi> with their Aid, having a Warrant from <hi>Simon Broadſtreet, in his Majeſty's Name</hi> (as they ſaid) <hi>to break up our Meeting;</hi> ſome Friends deſired them to read their Warrant, which was to this effect, <hi>That they were to bring every Perſon found at a</hi> Quakers <hi>Meeting;</hi> then a Friend ſaid, <hi>This Warrant is to bring ſuch Perſons as are found at a</hi> Quakers <hi>Meeting to the Houſe of Correction. Alice Curwen</hi> anſwered, <hi>This War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant takes not hold on us; we are the Meeting; this Warrant is to bring ſuch Perſons as are found at a</hi> Quakers <hi>Meeting.</hi> So the Conſtable ſtood pretty moderately; but <hi>Benj. Gibs</hi> turned about to a Friend in the Miniſtry, and ſaid, <hi>Come, ye are Blaſphemers; we will not ſtand to ſac the Devil Worſhipped:</hi> Then <hi>Benj. Gibs</hi> being asked, <hi>What he heard us ſay?</hi> His anſwer was, <hi>He had not heard us ſpeak one word;</hi> though before he had called us <hi>Blaſphemers,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>They would not ſtand there to ſee the Devil worſhipped. Alice Curwen</hi> (in the Fear of the Lord) kneeling down to Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, was violently haled along the Room and down Stairs to the Houſe of Correction.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Fluſhen</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> 
                        <date>the 6th of the 12th Moneth, 1677.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Thomas Curwen.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:31806:37"/>
            <p>The Sufferings of <hi>Thomas Curwen,</hi> which he hath ſuffered for Conſcience ſake towards God, which was for the Teſtimony of Jeſus, the Spirit of Prophecy, the Word of God, who have Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with ſeveral <hi>Prieſts</hi> concerning my Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony for the Tythe ever ſince I was convinced of the Eternal Truth of God, who doth Witneſs the Law changed, and the Prieſthood changed alſo, that took Tythes under the Law, which was an Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the time of the Law, before Chriſt came; but now Chriſt Jeſus is come, and I do witneſs him come, who is the one Offering, who was ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and offered up once for all, who hath Fulfilled and put an End to all Tythes, Types, Figures and Shadows, and Offerings under the Law of a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Command: but now I do witneſs (Glory be to God forever) Chriſt Jeſus come, who is the <hi>Power of God unto Salvation,</hi> who is a Prieſt forever, without Beginning or End of Days, who is <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega</hi> forever; and therefore I cannot pay Tythes.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Concerning my</hi> Sufferings <hi>and</hi> Perſecution <hi>by</hi> Thomas Shaw <hi>Prieſt of</hi> Aldingham <hi>in</hi> Fornis <hi>in</hi> Lancaſhire.</head>
                  <p>IN the year 1652. about the 14th day of the 7th moneth, I had a Mare taken away worth 6 <abbr>l.</abbr> alſo in the year 1654. I had a Cow taken away worth 2 <abbr>l.</abbr> 10 <abbr>s.</abbr> and in the year 1656. I had two Cows taken away worth 8 <abbr>l.</abbr> and in the year 1658. I had the moſt part of ſixteen Acres of Corn taken away, which was worth at leaſt 30 <abbr>l.</abbr> whoſe Bailiffs and Servants came forcibly &amp; brake into the Barn: and alſo in the year 1660. about the 10th day of the 11th moneth, I had a Horſe taken away
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:31806:38"/>worth 4 <abbr>l.</abbr> or there-about. And theſe Goods took Prieſt <hi>Shaw</hi> from me, beſides Eleaven Years Impriſonment; and then ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after he ended his dayes in great Wo and Miſery to the ſight of all the World that did know him; for the Lord laid his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon him, who was ſtruck into a Palſie, that he was not ſenſible what he did or ſaid.</p>
                  <p>And then another with his Horns began to puſh, and make War with the Lamb, as the Scripture declares, <hi>That the Beaſt and the Falſe Prophet ſhall make War with the Lamb, but the Lamb ſhall get the Victory,</hi> wherein the Redeemed of the Lord ſing Praiſes, Praiſes to the Lord God and the Lamb forever in the Land of the Living; for it is the Lamb of God that takes away the Sins of the World, and blotteth out the Hand-writing, and come to know their Names written in the Book of Life: And I am a Witneſs that the Promiſe of the Lord is fulfilled, where the Lord hath written his Law in our Hearts, and put his Spirit into our inward parts, wherein we can read in the Book of Life in the great Myſtery of Godſineſs, which is manifeſt in the Fleſh in this our Day; Praiſes to the Lord God and the Lamb forevermore.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Prieſt</hi>'s Name was <hi>Theophilus Ames,</hi> who continued in Perſecuting the Innocent; but the Lord ſhortned his dayes in a little time, he was ſo very Cruel; he ſent his Bailiffs to take away my Goods, who took ſixteen Beaſts at one time, which were worth 50 <abbr>l.</abbr> or there-about in the year 1665 about the 29th day of the 8th Moneth; and about the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the 5th moneth in the year 1667. my ſelf, my Wife &amp; my Son were taken to Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for not coming to their worſhip nor receiving the Sacrament, and carryed me to Priſon in a Cart, who was ſo ill that I could neither go nor ride on Horſe-back, who did carry me about twenty Miles, and did purpoſe to keep us in Priſon for term of Life; but the Lord did deliver us, who is a preſent Help in time of need to the Faithful and Upright in Heart, who are kept in his Fear; bleſſed for evermore be his holy and bleſſed Name, which is a ſtrong Tower for the Righteous to flee unto in time of Storm, when the <hi>Heathen</hi> rages, and the People imagin vain things: and after Prieſt <hi>Ames</hi> had caſt us into Priſon, in the year 1667. about the 29th of the 5th moneth the Prieſt cauſed
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:31806:38"/>to be taken from me eleaven Beaſts and one Horſe, which were worth about 40 <abbr>l.</abbr> and when he had taken theſe Beaſts he fell on to plunder the Houſe, and took all the Goods that he could get away, he took ſo near, that he took Garden-Mittans and the Cole-Rake; and when he had done this, then the meaſure of his Wickedneſs and Iniquity was filled up, and then the Lord ſhortly after ſhortned his dayes, who dyed a Woful and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Death; for the Lord laid his Judgments upon him, who wa both Blind and Mad before he dyed, to the great Admiration and aſtoniſhment of all that did ſee his Death.</p>
                  <p>And then another Beaſt with his Horns began to puſh, and to make War with the Lamb, as the Scripture declares, and bleſſed are they who are called to make War in Righteouſneſs; and if we put not into the falſe Prophets Mouthes, they will make War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us; and he that ſtands in the Gap makes himſelf a Prey.</p>
                  <p>The Prieſt's Name is <hi>Michael Stanford,</hi> who is driving on <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Charriots as faſt as he can, until the Lord ſhorten his dayes; for <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Heart was hardened when he did perſecute the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the dayes of old; and this Prieſt ſaid, <hi>That his Heart was hardened againſt us:</hi> And what became of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> when his Heart was hardened that he would not let <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> go? So all read that can; for the Lord God will ſhorten the dayes of the Wicked for the Elect Seed's ſake; for it was the full Intent and Purpoſe of my Heart to continue in this War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare about Tythes, and Contend for the Faith which was once delivered to the Saints, and to ſtand a faithful Witneſs for the Lord's Teſtimony againſt the Beaſt and the Falſe Prophet whilſt I had a being in this Earthly Tabernacle, until the Lord laid an Engagement upon me (wherein I durſt not diſobey) to go along with my dear Friend my Wife, to be her Companion for the Clearing of her Teſtimony, which the Lord had called her to; who did bear a faithful Teſtimony for the Lord, and hath laid down her Head in Peace.</p>
                  <p>And as for this Perſecuting Prieſt, theſe are his Actions, and the Fruits of his Miniſtry at this time, who about the 2d of the firſt moneth, 1674. did take from me my Brewing-pan; and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:31806:39"/>alſo in the year 1674. his Bailiffs took from me three Beaſts worth 8 <abbr>l.</abbr> and that which he called his Due was but about 6 <abbr>s.</abbr> So all People may ſee and know (whereſoever this may come) the Fruits of this Perſecuting Prieſt's Miniſtry.</p>
                  <p>Prieſt <hi>Stanford</hi>'s Tythe-mongers in the year 1673. took from me as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi> Upon the 4th day of the 7th moneth <hi>James Chambers</hi> came forcibly, and broke into a Field of Corn of mine, and broke down the Hedge in ſeveral places, and took the Corn out of the Field before I took, and before one part of the Field was reapt, contrary to the Law of the Nation.</p>
                  <p>And alſo, <hi>James Chambers</hi> did break into another Corn-Field of mine upon the 11th day of the 7th moneth, who broke down the Hedge in ſeveral places, and did carry the Corn away before I took any.</p>
                  <p>And at another time <hi>James Chambers, Thomas Chamblay</hi> and <hi>James Geldert,</hi> went through a Field of Corn before the moſt of it was reapt, contrary to the Law of the Nation.</p>
                  <p>And alſo on another day <hi>James Geldert</hi> came, and broke into a Corn-Field of mine, and did break down the Hedge, and carryed away the Corn, contrary to the Law of the Nation.</p>
                  <p>And upon another day <hi>James Geldert</hi> came, and broke into a Field of Corn, and broke down the Hedge, and took away the Corn, contrary to theLaw of the Nation.</p>
                  <p>And alſo <hi>John Hawood,</hi> who rented the Fines, cauſed a Horſe to be taken from me for a Fine of 15 <abbr>s.</abbr> which was worth 4 <abbr>l.</abbr> which was for Conſcience ſake towards God in Obedience to his holy Command.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Bailiffs</hi> Names by whom Prieſt <hi>Shaw</hi> canſed my Body to be impriſoned, and my Goods to be taken away, were theſe, viz. <hi>Will. Garner, John Garner, Tho. Marſhall, James Poſtelwhete, Tho. Poolton, Chriſtopher Garner, John Poolton, Miles Fell, James Garner, Richard Fell, Will. Fell, John Sanford.</hi> The Conſtables Names, viz. <hi>John Garner, Chriſtopher Chamblay, Timothy Mount, Leonard Cooper</hi> and <hi>Luke Benſon</hi> Bailiff.</p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:31806:39"/>
                  <p>Prieſt <hi>Ames</hi> his Bailiffs Names, viz. <hi>William Struckland, Geo. Askew, William Garner, Tho. Poope, Thomas Poolton. James Chambers</hi> was Prieſt <hi>Ames</hi> his Conſtable to aſſiſt the Bailiffs for the Plundering of my Houſe, and let the Prieſt have a Houſe to put the plundered Goods in; and this Conſtable did provide a Horſe and a Cart to carry me to Priſon.</p>
                  <p>Prieſt <hi>Stanford</hi>'s Bailiffs Names, viz. <hi>William Struckland, George Askew, John Garner, Richard Fell, Luke Benſon,</hi> and alſo <hi>Roger Woodborn,</hi> who was the Steward of the Court and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Judge; there was a Jury appointed, but he did not put the Action to the Jury, but paſſed Judgment on it himſelf; but the Lord ſhortned his dayes, that he never tryed more Actions, but dyed ſhortly.</p>
                  <p>Oh! that all People would take Warning and Repent, leſt they provoke the Lord to anger, and they periſh in his Wrath! for the Indignation of the Lord burns like Fire againſt the Wicked and Ungodly upon the Earth, who is a Conſuming Fire to the Wicked.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>THOMAS CURWEN.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
